Hello again
In this video, I'm going to tell you about Pointer Arithmetics.
I hope you're focused, because this is usually the moment where people drop out.
You'll see, it's quite simple really, but for some mysterious reason,
people usually struggle with these notions...
Let's do this!
Here's the main I've prepared.
I've declared "a" and "b", both ints. I've assigned values to those variables,
and then I'm using self-made functions to display the address of "a",
and then display its value. And then same for "b" (address then value)
Let's see what happens.
See, we have the address of "a" and "b".
Notice how similar those addresses are?
"a" is actually 4 bytes further from "b". That's normal.
I told you about the stack earlier. And when you declare objects on the stack...
- the stack is actually all the way at the top of the addresses -
... so when you declare something on the stack, you go through addresses downwards.
The difference between "a" and "b" is 4, because an int is 4 bytes.
So here you go. The address of "a" is 4 bytes away from the address of "b".
Now that I'm aware of this, I'll be able to use pointers to move to "a" and to "b".
Let's create a pointer "*ptr".
and "ptr = &b;" (the address of "b")
Yes. I've selected b's address,
as I told you, "b" is after "a" on the stack, but the address comes first...
that's just how it is.
If I wanted to do the exact same thing here, I'd have to write this...
That used to be "a"'s address ("&a"), "ptr" being the address of "b"
you'd think we could write "ptr + 4", as "b" is 4 bytes away from "a"...
But our compiler is smarter than that. It knows "ptr" is a pointer to int.
So when you type "ptr" + a value, it multiplies this value by the size of an int
It's logical for you to move int by int,
so to go from "b" to "a", I'd have to type "ptr + 1".
Now. Here I used to display the value of "a"...
To display the value of the pointed object, we used an asterisk.
So "*ptr" should display the value of "b".
But now I can do "ptr + 1".
Normally I should be allowed to do this.
So what does that mean?
It means I'm taking the address contained within "ptr", I'm gonna do +1,
the compiler knows it's a pointer to int, so it's going to add 4 bytes,
and this asterisk means "check out what's at this new address".
Logically, I should display the address of "a", and its value (3).
Even though I'm using "ptr", which points to "b"
Recompiling. Relaunching.
Here you go. If you compare this to our previous result,
I've displayed the address of "a".
Wait, there's a slight difference... That's odd...
Oh yeah, that's because I recompiled and relaunched the program,
so it doesn't have the EXACT same address...
But that's okay. What's important is that I am indeed displaying "a"'s address,
even though I used "b"'s address.
'Cause addresses can change every time you relaunch a program.
But that's another story.
Now that we've done this, I want to show you that it's different with "chars" ...
So imagine I change my int here and replace it with a char,
So "char a", "char b" and instead of "ptr" pointing to an int,
I'm going to make it point to a char.
I need to change this because I can't use 3 anymore as it requires characters...
so I'm going to use the ASCII character '3' for "a", just to mess with you.
I'm going to use the ASCII character 'o' for "b",
and here, I'm going to replace "ft_putnbr" by "ft_putchar",
because we want to display characters.
So here, normally, I have "a" with the ASCII value of '3',
"b" with the ASCII value of 'o',
"ptr" that points to "b",
"ptr + 1", which should be the address of "b" + 1.
Yes. A char is one byte.
So when you move from char to char, we move byte by byte.
Just to show you, I'm going to add extra lines.
I'm taking the address of "b",
I'm going to display the address of "b".
And then I'll display the rest.
... typing ...
Recompiling & relaunching
As you can see, "ptr + 1" (one byte because we're using chars)
and we can do this with any type of variable.
And every time you do, the computer knows the variable's size you're pointing to.
So it'll be able to "move" accordingly.
Last detail... Just for laughs.
Let's use ints again.
I'm going to change the value of "a" to 1, the value of "b" to 42.
We'll keep what displays the address of "b".
And change "ptr + 1" into "ptr + a". You can 'call' a pointer with an int.
It's the same as 1. 1 being a static variable.
Let's check out the output.
The address of "b" is displayed. Same for the address of "a'.
And I forgot to display something...
I forgot to change my ft_putchar into a ft_putnbr...
See, I've displayed 1, which is the value of "a" from "ptr" which pointed to "b".
We've covered Pointer Arithmetics. See it wasn't that complicated, was it?
Just remember that you can do calculations with an address,
and then use an asterisk to check what's at this address.