Hello again.
In this video, we'll talk about character strings.
We've see what a character was.
so here's a example of main with a character "c".
I gave "char c" the ASCII value for " * ".
So if I do a putchar of "char c",
it should display an asterisk onscreen
compiling... launching. All good!
In a previous video, I made a mistake... remember? I used quotation marks...
instead of inverted comas.
quotation marks are for character strings.
So, what's a character string?
It's an ensemble of bytes, one byte next to the other.
So a series of bytes each containing one character.
And normally,
this string's last element should be "\0" or the value "0",
the ASCII character for "\0" or "0", they're all the same thing.
Actually, for each ASCII character,
there's a "numerical value" that defines the end of the string.
How could we use this?
It's simple.
When you type "Toto", it'll be replaced by the address
of 1st element of the character string "toto".
Which is the address of "t".
Be careful...
I just spoke about addresses...
We're talking about pointers.
You're probably telling yourself "Okay, we're going to need a pointer"
This time I'm going to call it "*str".
Nah, actually I'm going to call it "*ptr", it'll be better.
It's the same thing, we're still talking about pointers.
I'm going to write something that the Norm forbids...
Actually, no, that'll just be confusing.
So "ptr" equals to the address of the "toto" character string.
I told you a few seconds ago
that "Toto" is a series of bytes, one after the other, that ends with a "\0"
and so when we write "Toto",
the character string "Toto", we simply return the address of the 1st character
"ptr" can only contain an address.
That's an important fact.
From now on, and for the rest of the video,
we will talk about character strings.
But remember,
when we talk about a pointer to string (character string of course)
In a way, it's still a pointer to char.
It's a pointer to the first element of the character string.
Let's just hope that in the end,
when you go through your bytes, thanks to pointers arithmetics,
all the way at the end, you'll have a "\0"
that'll tell you to stop.
But when you write this,
the compiler will automatically set "toto" in its memory
So char "t", char "o", char "t", char "o" AND char "\0"
and will return the address of the first character, so "t".
Here's the proof.
If I display "*ptr" - the element pointed by "ptr"
See, here's my "t".
Remember, I told you about another way to write this,
which is easier...
Using square brackets.
This should give me the exact same result.
See, still "t".
So if I wanted to move around my string "toto",
The last element of the string, as we said earlier,
when I told you to allocate 10 elements on the stack, with an array,
so the last element is the 9th element. Exactly.
So how many elements have I allocated for tToto"? Truely?
Nope, not 4! I'm sure everybody thought 4...
It's 5!
I told you earlier there was an extra "\0" at the end...
So in reality, I have 5 on the stack.
But the "\0" is something special...
Because it'll allow us to know when we're done browsing through memory,
and that we're done reading the character string.
So when you'll create character strings, manually, you must remember
to always end your string with a "\0".
Otherwise, all programs that can read character strings, will keep reading,
until they find a "\0". And it could crash.
"crashing" = bad!
So. "ptr[0]". If I wanted to access the last "o",
"ptr[1]" is the first "o", "ptr[2]" is the second "t",
"ptr[3]" that's the last "o".
Let's display it.
See!
Cool! I've displayed the last "o".
If I try to display "ptr[4]"...
(as I've said, we have 5 elements on the stack)
This is what happens.
It doesn't display anything, sort of.
Let's use the "cat" command on it.
With the "-e" option, which displays non-printable characters.
See those characters on screen? They represent "\0".
A simple character string.
So I've successfully displayed the end of the "toto" character string.
Something very important you should know,
When you write this...
you've been given an address.
But "toto" is somewhere in memory, where you're not allowed to write.
Meaning that if I wanted to transform "toto" into "poto"...
If I write this ... (types)
Normally, it should either not compile at all,
or compile, but crash...
"Bus error". I've crashed.
Yay! That's exactly what I wanted to show you.
"toto" here, is in an area where we're not allowed to write.
The only way for me to write over "toto", would be to declare an array,
but without setting its size. Look at what I'm typing.
Once you've done this, the compiler knows you're trying
to allocate an array, and that you want to write "toto" in it,
so it'll allocate 5 elements, (t, o, t, o, \0)
and it'll put those 5 elements' address on the stack,
and "ptr" will be a pointer on that.
So if I do the same thing, see?
let's compile & execute.
This time it worked, I have "p" as my string's 1st element.
All of this seems fun for now...
But I wanted to show you something to make things clearer.
30 seconds ago, we had "char *ptr"
and underneath "ptr = "toto;"
What happens if I add another "char *",
let's call it "ptr2".
and then write " ptr2 = "lol"; "
and then write "ptr = ptr2;"
What happens when I check "ptr[0]"?
Well it's simple...
If we follow the logic,
"ptr2" takes the address of "l" from "lol" & "ptr" takes the address of "toto"'s "t"
Now. When I write "ptr = ptr2",
on the right I have a pointer to char, on the left, I have a pointer to char...
I'm allowed to write this.
So what's "ptr2"? It's just an address.
"ptr" also is an address.
So I've overwritten the address contained in "ptr",
by the address contained in "ptr2".
So the result is that "ptr" now points to the "l" (from "lol").
So normally, if I execute this...
I've displayed an "l".
So that's about everything you need to know about character strings.
Just remember. A character string is a series of bytes (or characters),
one after another, and that ends with a "\0".