Hello once again!
We're going to conclude
this "pointers day"
with pointers' usage.
So far, we've only
played with pointers
within a main, or a function
and you probably don't see the point.
But as soon as you'll know how to allocate memory,
you'll understand their importance.
Because so far,
we've named things on the stack.
Every time we have a variable "a",
and a variable "b", we get their addresses.
That's too bad,
because we only know where they are
but soon, we'll be able to say
"Hello, gimme some memory"
without having to name them.
That's where pointers come into play.
Here's a simple example
of pointer usage,
that'll be extremely useful
for today's lesson.
We have a function, a main, rather,
and a function fct().
In my main, I've declared an int "a",
with the value "42".
Then I called my function fct(),
with "a" as a parameter.
Then I'll display "a"'s value
in my main,
then display a "\n" and return 0.
What will my function fct() do?
It takes an int as parameter,
that we've called "a",
and I'll set its value to 12.
What do you think will happen
when I execute this program?
What will be displayed?
12 or 42?
Let's test this...
You'll never be able to break the machine,
so don't hesitate to run tests.
42 is displayed.
Let's go back to our code.
"a", here, is the "a" from my main.
Its value is 42.
Know that by passing a parameter,
we always pass it "by copy"...
Basically, here I didn't pass "a",
but a copy of "a"'s value.
So the "a" that's here,
is not the same. It's my function's "a".
So here, the "a" possesses a copy
of the first "a", that's in my main.
Therefore, it took the value of "42".
When I modify this, "a = 12",
I'm modifying the "a" from my function.
But the "a" from my main
hasn't changed!
Once again, we did not pass it
the "a" from my main,
we passed it a copy of its value.
So how can we manage,
in my function,
to modify the value of "a" in my main?
Well, instead of copying
the value of "a",
I'm going to copy the address of "a".
And here, instead of having an int,
otherwise, it won't compile,
as I'm passing it an int's address,
so here, we'd need to turn it
into a pointer to int.
My "a" becomes a pointer to int,
and if I want to change the value of "a",
so the value pointed by
my function's "a",
I'm going to have to dereference here.
Normally, if you've watched
the other videos,
this notion should be clear.
So I'm calling my function,
by passing the address of "a",
so made a copy of the address of "a"
which goes into a pointer to int
also called "a",
(just to confuse you)
then I've decided that the value
pointed by this "a",
would take the value 12.
Let's see what happens.
Here we go!
It now has 12 for value!
The purpose of pointers
is to be able to either move around an array,
either move around a character string,
(which is an array of "char"s)
either pass a variable's address
and modify it in a function.
That's one of the most common use of pointers.
This concludes our lesson on pointers.
If you struggle with these notions,
don't hesitate to watch these videos again
but mostly, try it out for yourselves.
As I've said before, you can't break the machine.
read error messages,
the compiler is here to help.
Good day and good luck.