♫ ( TIME TO PLAY THE GAME ! ) ♫
Hello. In this video, we'll talk about arrays.
Actually, earlier on, we've seen we could declare "a" and "b" on the stack,
and that we could go from one to the other
because they're almost stored in the same place.
Now. I'd like to have 10 ints
rather than declare 10 variables
like a,b,c,d,e,f,g... etc till I have 10,
I'd like to declare a variable that possesses 10 ints 'within'
That's called an array.
Here's a piece of code used earlier
We could declare an int by writing "int b"
Now I'm gonna call it "tab"
and you're going to discover a new syntax.
When I write "int tab[10]",
I'm saying that on the stack, there'll be 10 ints
And that "tab" will be some sort of implicit pointer
on the first of these ints
We're still using pointers
Now, look : Here, in "putaddr",
I used to give it an address,
Here I'm going to give it "tab" instead.
And if I want to display one of tab's numbers,
so far I haven't set any...
we'll be able to access one of tab's elements
by using square brackets ( [ ] )
For example, the first element is "tab[0]"
You'll understand why in a moment.
First, let me show you that it works.
Compiling & executing
We can see that "tab" is an address
And that "tab[0]" has the value '42'.
Now let me explain why the first element of "tab" is "tab[0]",
Basically, "tab[something]" is like writing " *( tab + brackets' content ) "
When I write this ...
see these two lines?
"tab[0] = 42;", or *(tab + 0) = 42
It's the exact same thing.
Let me prove it to you.
Re-compiling, re-launching.
I still have the value "42".
I told you that "tab" was some sort of pointer,
that points towards the 1st element of an array of ints.
When I do "+ 0", it's the address of the first element
and when I do *(tab + 0)
I get an int which is the 1st element on my array.
So "tab[0]" and "*(tab + 0)" are the exact same thing,
If I wanted to access the 4th element,
Well I'd do "tab + 3".
("tab + 0" for the 1st, "tab + 1" for the 2nd, "tab + 2" for the 3rd, etc...
Remember in a previous video ?
Normally with "+ 3" , as we're using ints,
by taking their real size into account,
it's actually "+ 12" : " + 3 * 4 bytes "
because an int = 4 bytes.
So I've used both "*(tab + 3)" and "tab[3]".
And it works.
So here I have a memory slot that's allocated 10 elements.
If the first element is at "+ 0",
the last is at ...
"+ 9"!
And not at "+ 10".
Be careful.
When you have an array of 10 elements,
the last element is the array's length "- 1"
to access it.
Because, in order to access the first element,
we access it by "0".
Now that we've seen this,
I'm going to prove that it is indeed a pointer.
So imagine... I'm going to use "*ptr"
and do "ptr = tab;"
"tab" being an address.
(I hope it compiles)
It does. All good.
So "ptr" has taken tab's value
Reminder: "tab" is an address.
the address of the first element of the array I allocated.
So if I do "*(ptr + 3)"
"ptr + 3" is an address
"*(ptr + 3)" is an int
Let's give it a value, such as 867,
and here I'll display "tab[3]"
Will it work ...?
867. All good!
See, arrays are just another way
of writing pointers arithmetics more simply.
and (at the top) it also allows us to declare more elements
Just to be thorough, let me show you something else.
Let's make an array of ints...
and underneath, I'm going to create an array containing two elements
... actually, let's add more things.
This one, I shall call "tabptr".
It'll contain 2 pointers to int.
It's an array of pointers to int.
And we could do this to infinity
(pointer to pointer to pointer to...)
Let's imagine now...
I want to modify "tab2" from "tabptr"...
"tabprt[0]" is a pointer to int
so it'll take an int's address.
solet's give it tab's value.
"tabptr[1]" is equal to "tab2"
and now I want to modify "tab2[3]" through "tabptr".
- I've linked tabptr[0] -
To check out tab2[3], it's easy...
tabptr[1] represents "tab2"
and now, [3],
if I set the value to 42, it should work.
Let's remove what we don't need.
Let's give it a shot...
Sorry this video is so long...
The value of "tab2[3]" has been set to 42.
You'll see that this is all very logical.
How could I rewrite this with pointers?
And this is the last thing we'll see in this video.
So. How could I rewrite this with pointers?
As I've said, when you do : "something[something]"
it's the same thing as doing : " *(what's on the left + what's in brackets) "
So I'm going to transform "tabptr[1][3]"
into something with asterisks.
Let's start by moving the "[3]" and add an asterisk.
What's on the left of "[3]'? it's "tabptr[1]".
so "+ 3".
That, is equal to 42.
Normally those two lines do the same.
Let's test this.
Still displaying 42.
Now let's do the same with "[1]".
Recompiling... Relaunching...
Still displaying 42.
The point I wanted to make ...
The line bellow is equivalent to this.
So, the point I wanted to make ...
We said that "tabptr" was an array of pointers to int.
And I said earlier that "tab" was an array of ints.
So "tab" is some sort of pointer to int.
So "tabptr" is some sort of pointer to pointer to int.
And you can clearly see that.
'cause in order to access my int, (to set its value to 42)
I had to use two asterisks.
1st time, I took the address contained in "tabptr" and added 1.
- talks about bytes -
I checked what was at this address.
At this address, we actually have "tab2"
and then I added "+ 3" to "tab2"
and also checked what was at this address.
So it's as if I wrote "tab2[3]" and gave it the value 42.
Here you go, those were the basics of arrays.
Beware...
Sorry, I'm almost done.
Beware... If I write this... (look onscreen)
"tab" is NOT a pointer to pointer to int.
Be really careful with this.
Basically, behind your array, there's a pointer to int.
You can access it in the function, using two square brackets,
but as soon as you want to pass it another function, you'll have problems.
You'll have to try things with arrays of arrays.
But now that you've seen how to make array pointers, and
simple arrays, arrays of ints, arrays of pointers to (...) ints,
it's up to you to practice and test things.
That's it.