Recursion is a programming method,
that's completely different from what you've seen so far.
What you've learnt so far, is what we call :
Iterative programming
Iterative programming is a programming technique
that uses instruction loops that repeat themselves,
that evaluate to nothing,
and that uses what we call side effects
in order to return values
meaning they use variables.
Let's use your FT_strlen() as an example.
(I hope you've done it!)
that takes a variable, initialises it to 0,
and does a loop that, at each iteration,
(note iteration: iterative programming, and all)
will increase your variable by 1.
So it's using an external variable
in order to return its result.
Its result - it doesn't really return one -
is stored within a variable.
Iterative programming is exactly like this.
The ft_strlen() is a canonical example.
Recursive programming is a little different.
You have to picture it just like Russian dolls...
We'll have functions calling themselves, and then
they call themselves again, and call themselves again,
and call themselves again, etc...
Up to a certain point
where we'll use mechanisms to return results.
In order to understand this, you must first understand
the principles of a pile.
and by "pile", I mean the stack.
It's a program's reserved region of memory
that'll fill up as we call functions,
that's pretty much empty
at the beginning of the program
For example,
let's use a simple program,
at the very beginning, the stack is empty
when we start the program, the main is called,
so the function "main" will be put on the stack.
We could also say that it's pushed onto the stack.
And then, somewhere in your code,
the main will call your ft_putstr().
Therefore, we call ft_putstr(), that'll also be added to the stack.
And somewhere in ft_putstr()'s code,
ft_putchar() will also be called, and therefore will also be added to the stack.
ft_putchar() will then call "write", which will also be added onto the stack.
etc, etc...
Basically, every time we call a function,
this function will be pushed onto the stack, it'll evaluate itself,
and, at some point, when we're done with our function,
we'll return to our previous function.
Our function that was on top of the stack,
will be removed from the stack, we can also say that it's popped from the stack,
so our function will be gone, and be replaced by the previous one.
In our example, we'll remove "write" and ft_putchar() will remain.
and our execution will come back to ft_putchar().
We'll keep going and remove ft_putchar(), and go back to ft_putstr().
Then go back to the main, etc...
As I said before, it's just like Russian dolls.
Functions pile up on top of each other,
or within one another,
and that's the principle we'll use for recursive functions.
A recursive function, is a function that calls itself
and that pushes itself on the stack, on top of itself.
In principle, it's not that complicated.
However, we'll do this until
we reach two possible outcomes:
either you have a function that's okay with always
just calling itself, in which case
every time it'll finish its action, we'll re-push another instance
of our function onto the stack.
And as you can imagine, if we don't stop it,
the stack will grow, and grow...
till it goes "ka-boom!"
The program will crash, because your system will inform it
that it's gone over the stack's capacity, (the one allocated to it)
and as you can imagine, that wasn't such a brilliant idea.
The second possible output, in this kind of situation,
and that's what we normally should do,
when we use recursion properly,
is to get to a point in our execution
where there's a stopping condition.
And tell ourselves, at some point in our function,
let's call it fn(), which is a function that calls itself,
that there's a condition that states that if a criteria is met,
then we can stop calling it, and return it instead.
It's as if you said:
"Enough, I'm stopping now. I'm not going to keep on
using recursion, otherwise the stack will break down".
It's the same principle as a stopping condition in a loop.
Actually, it's exactly the same principle.
Except that it's being implemented differently.
So when we reach our stopping condition,
we stop pilling up functions onto the stack.
we pop the functions,
and we go down the stack to return to our initial state.
Now, let's check out a small mathematical example (on Vim).
I know everybody's not a fan of math,
but in the case, the example is appropriate.
Let's talk about factorial functions,
for those of you who haven't done math in a while,
or those that have a selective memory,
a factorial function can be written
as follows:
Factorial 5 = 5 x 4 x 3 x 2 x 1. (x = multiplication)
Same goes for 6 : 6 x 5 x 4 x 3 x 2 x 1.
I'm sure you get it.
I can show you with another couple of factorial,
factorial 4 = 4 x 3 x 2 x 1.
factorial 3 = 3 x 2 x 1.
And if you think about it,
we could say that factorial 5 is like doing 5 x 4!
or factorial 4 is the same as 3! multiplied by 4.
I could go on like this forever. Or till I reach factorial 1.
Simple fact: factorial 1, is 1.
Notice the resemblance with recursion?
We can see that 5! = 5 x 4!,
4! = 4 x 3!,
all the way to 1! = 1,
which is kind of a stopping condition.
Just in case it's not clear enough yet,
let's say that for n > 0,
n! = n x (n - 1) x (n - 2) x , etc...
until 3 x 2 x 1.
Base on this example, we could say that:
factorial n = n x factorial (n - 1),
Easy peasy, right?
So factorial(n - 1) is equal to (n - 1) x factorial(n - 2)
etc, etc...
till we reach 1. Which will end our recursion.
That was a form of recursion.
Written in math, granted, but still.
I'm going to show you recursion in code. Not in C though,
that'd be too easy. But in pseudo-code ;)
We can write that the function fact(N) is equal to N x fact(N -1).
Therefore it's a recursive function, and it need a stopping condition.
As you now know, the factorial for 1 is equal to 1.
From this example, you should be able to build a recursion,
with a stopping condition, that'll execute,
without making your program explode.
At least I hope so...
So. In order to calculate the factorial N, we need to calculate that of (N - 1), etc.
It looks a bit like a loop... And it could be written as such.
You'll have to do it anyway.
Let's stop for now, and see you in the next video,
for more examples in real C code.