Hello everyone,
and welcome to d04 of C Bootcamp.
Today's topic: Recursion.
Recursion is a programming concept
that might seem strange at first for some of you.
But we'll divide this lesson into two parts.
First part: Theory:
What is it and how will it change my life?
but most importantly, why should I care about recursion?
and then, second part, Practice:
We'll check out a mathematical example first,
then in real code.
To see how it works in real life.
make sure, before starting this lesson,
that you really understand how functions work:
how to call a function,
how to pass it parameters,
how to make it return values,
how it's evaluated, etc...
If you didn't get these facts,
I strongly advise you to revise
these notions before starting these videos.
Otherwise, you might get lost,
and end up wasting your time.
Let's get started.