Now that we've seen the theory, let's move on to practice with examples.
If you'll allow me, I'm going to begin with examples that don't work at all...
Because I'd rather make those mistakes myself, in front of you,
to show you what not to do, rather than you making them yourselves.
So, I'm going to apply what I did in the previous video. Literally.
I'm going to create a recursive function, and call it "fn()".
For a function to be recursive, it needs to call itself.
There.
That's it.
I've created a self-calling function.
I'm going to create a main, calling fn() too.
This program won't be doing much...
Let's add "return (0)", 'cause we're civilised
There...
I'm going to compile this, and you'll see, it won't display much, but it'll do something fun.
Segfault ! But why?
If you paid attention during the 1st video (and had I remembered what I said 10min ago)
we'd remember that a function needs a stopping condition. Otherwise...
we put in on the stack...
it calls itself, we put in on the stack...
and again and again (x6) ...
And at some point,
IT
BLOWS
UP
IN
OUR
FACES
because we've exceeded the stack's size.
We mustn't do this.
You'll be surprised.
So now, I'm wondering... Maybe I should add a stopping condition...
so that my function doesn't call itself endlessly.
So... I don't know... Let's start by adding a variable?
I'm used to this... So let's add a variable here,
then initialise it to 0 to have a counter.
Then, let's make an experiment.
If "i <= 5", then I'll call "fn()"
Else, I'll return 0.
Okay?
And before calling fn(), I'm going to increment my "i", else it'll never increase
it'll remain at 0 and my thingy won't ever work.
Let's be logical.
I'm going to compile this thing. It should work, right?
Hmmmm... "warning"... that's alright...
Nope, actually it doesn't work...
That's ridiculous, right?
Sooo... What could I have possibly done wrong?
That's right!
Look at the function. Look closely.
I go into my function, I declare an "i", I say "i = 0;", okay.
I check whether "i <= 5". Well we know it's 0. So I increment it and call fn().
So I go back into fn() for another loop, and then ...
Oh right! I declare a variable, set it to 0... Of course it doesn't work!
'Cause remember: I put fn() on the stack, it's got its own context and variables,
so it's got its "i" that's worth 0, then it increases to 1, then i call back fn(),
so I add another fn() on the stack, that's got its own context and its own variables
... see where I'm going with this?
So my second fn() also has its own "i", which is set to 0, and it's worth 1,
and therefore isn't worth 5... So I call it. And again, and again...
You get my drift.
So how could we fix this?
Remember the basics of C? The parts about passing parameters and return values?
You know that there's a way to pass values between functions. So what could we do?
We could... not declare our "i" here, but instead, pass it as a parameter!
Here we could test it.
Actually, I'm going to add a return(0), "warning" once is fun, twice, it's rotten.
Then I'll pass my present "i" to my newer calling of fn(),
I'm going to call it with 0 in my main(). To start by 0.
So I'm gonna have fn() with 0. It's worth less than 5, so I'll increase it by 1,
then call fn() with its new value (1)
Now. I have an fn() with 1. Still worth less than 5. So let's increment it.
It now calls an fn(), that's now worth 2. And that's the behavior I wanted!
So to show you it works, let me first add a write() of "D" for "demo" or "display".
Right here, before calling my function.
Let's compile.
Here we go!
It displays "D" six times... Why six?
Because I went from 0 to 5. Included.
So that's 6.
As it displays "D" six times, it proves my function was called 6 times exactly.
That's what I wanted!
Let me show you one last example to illustrate the principles of stack calling
I'm just gonna add another write().
A write() of "F" for "finished!", right after a call to fn().
So there are two options... Either it'll display "DF" 6 times,
either it'll display something else.
In your opinion, what will be displayed?
Let's see...
Personally, I don't know. I'll find out with you!
What will be displayed?
Well, six times D and six times F.
Why do you think that is?
The reason is very simple.
At the beginning, I'm "pushing" my fn() on the stack, so it executes up to a point,
there's a write(D). Then a call to fn(). So I did a write(D) , then called fn().
a second fn() goes over my fn(), which isn't finished yet...
I add one on top.
I execute till it displays "D".
I call fn() again, etc...
I display "D". I call fn(), etc, etc...
After a while, I stop calling fn().
I go back.
I get back to my old fn() which was called by fn(). It finishes,
So write(F) happens.
So after displaying all Ds, I'll now display F, then return,
display f and return, display F and return etc, etc...
Till I reach the bottom of my pile calling fn(), then return to my main() and exit my program.
There you go. That's an example of a recursive function. That doesn't do much,
but it works perfectly. It has a stop-condition that works.
It displays what we ask without problems.
And if you look closely, you'll notice, in the end, it looks like a loop...
I've got "instruction blocks", and a counter. My instructions are repeated.
Recursion and iteration are quite different.
You can do many things with both.
Some operations are easier with iteration,
others much simpler with recursion.
You'll learn with experience.
There are two things to remember from this video.
... about recursive functions.
A recursive function is...
1) a function that calls itself
2) it has a stopping condition
(especially if you don't want it to blow up in your face)
And if you use counters. Make sure to relay them between each function's instances.
(parameters & return values)
That's all for today! So good luck for today's exercises...
You're gonna need it!
Till next time!