In this second part of D02, we're gonna talk about program arguments.
You know that "ls" can take "-l" in order to display details
of a directory.
What you've learnt to do, so far,
is launching your binary.
But if you added arguments, nothing would change.
Let me just quickly rewrite my Super Main.
I'm going to display "bonjour" ("hello" in French)
I think we can all agree to say that
whether I do this or that,
it'll always display the same thing.
You don't know how to retrieve what I wrote. Yet.
and by that, I mean the parameters that
your binary could take.
We told you that your main could take
two arguments...
It's thanks to those that you'll be able
to retrieve the parameters that can be passed to your binary.
ARGC represents the number of parameters
that you can pass to your program, while ARGV is a char**
in other words, a string array.
Which will contain those parameters.
So, I'm going to display
my first parameter,
and then a line break.
Re-compiling...
Here I can see that even without arguments, "a.out" is displayed.
Because your string array's first element
is your binary's name.
If I launched my binary from somewhere else,
argv[0] would have that binary's path and its name.
So in argv's first box, you have the binary's name,
the first element on your command line.
If I want my first argument,
I have to access to argv[1].
But if I don't set an argument, I'll get a segfault.
We cannot read in an empty array.
However, if I do this, it works.
If I do that, still works!
But if I do this ...
I'll only display the 1st argument.
the tric is to use inverted comas
to regroup multiple arguments within one same string.
We could say that ARGC is always, at least, equal to 1,
as argv[0] is always filled.
Then you'll be able to pass options to argv[1],
just like "ls" does
with its option "-l", or any other binary with options.
All of this will allow you to be a little more efficient in your program,
because you'll be able to use conditions.
For example, let's ask for argv[1] to be displayed,
only if ARGC is equal to 2.
This way we avoid a segfault
because we're testing whether there's an argument present.
and we allow it to be displayed, if it exists.
This way we don't need to test whether this string exists.
Thanks to ARGC, we can know how many arguments we have.
We can also use ARGC to display,
one by one, parameters passed to your program,
by scanning the array.
This could also allow us
to indicate whether the program needs an argument
and in the case where they don't exist,
tell the user
that the program needs
a certain number of arguments.
We can also warn them that the program
takes "toto" as an argument.
This way you can inform the user
on how to use your program properly.
With these examples, you can begin to imagine
the number of possibilities available to you, to make your program
more user-friendly.
Still... Watch out for segfaults. They'll force you to anticipate what
the user might try to do...
Up till now, you didn't have this constraint.
You'd launch your binary, being sure that you, and only you,
could choose how it behaves.
But now that you're allowing other users to interact with your program,
you'll never be sure of what they'll try and pass as arguments...
But we know what we're doing, and
we know what you might forget.
So here's a piece of advice:
Be careful, and bear in mind
that you'll never be able to guess everything the user
might pass to your program.
So test your arguments thoroughly, and check everything you do.