Hello everyone,
Today we're going to learn a couple of new things.
The first thing will be libraries. What are those for?
how to create them, but most importantly
how will they be useful for this C bootcamp?
(and for anything you do later on in C)
In short, "libraries" are a set of built-in functions,
constants and header files, gathered into one place.
You can create your own libraries to gather useful functions
so you don't have to waste time,
re-writing them every time you need them.
More details to come in the next videos.
The second thing we'll talk about,
is how to retrieve a program's arguments.
Up till now, we've been using mains without arguments.
But actually we can use mains that take arguments!
That's really useful: it allows us to compile our program just once,
instead of having to recompile every time we change something.
Therefore it makes your program more efficient.
Your program will be conditional,
so you won't have to recompile every time you want it
to have a different behavior.
So let's learn how to retrievea program's argument(s).