Hello, and welcome to D07 of the C bootcamp.
We're now going to explore the stages of compilation
Up till now, you were used to
compiling your files.c
to get an executable.
Let's start with an example. Here's my main.c,
with a putstr and a putchar.
It needs both to compile.
So we compile main.c with ft_putchar and ft_putstr.
It'll produce an executable "j07" (d07), with the "-o" option.
Let's launch "j07", which displays "42", followed by a line break.
Let's now divide this compilation into two stages.
In the first stage we'll compile our files.c in computer langage...
files.c to files.o
And then we'll go through another stage, called "linkage"
where we'll use the files.o to generate an executable.
Let's delete "j07" and compile our files, one by one, with the "-c" option.
which will just do the compiling.
For example, let's start with "ft_putstr".
It compiles. We don't have an executable upon completion, but ft_putstr.o is here.
Same thing for ft_putchar. Then with main.c
So we have putchar.o, putstr.o and main.o.
All that's left to do is to link those files.o.
still "j07" as the executable's name.
We get the same thing. Why do we do this?
If you've started working on bigger projects...
... with many files and functions,
This will allow you to take your files one by one and only recompile
the file you've modified. By using your Makefile.
If we modified ft_putchar.c, we could simply just recompile it's .o ...
I've recompiled my putchar.c into a .o, then re-link with my files.o
into a new executable.
This will allow you to go much faster, and to compile less code each time,
instead of recompiling everything.