Hello, and welcome to D08 of the C bootcamp.
Today we're going to talk about the preprocessor.
In D07's last video, you've learnt about the stages of compilation.
The first stage being the preprocessor,
the second being the compilation of files.c, and then you saw 'linkage'.
The preprocessor will allow you to generate code,
and set defines for what we call macros.
You've probably heard of those. In Excel, perhaps.
And that'll also allow you to protect you files from multiple inclusions.
And we'll end these videos with structures :
a new way to 'package' data,
as well as "typedef" which will allow you to create your own types of variables.