Hello,
In this video, I'm going to show you how to use preprocessor commands
in order to remove or add "code" elements to a file.c, for example.
This will often get used in files.h,
and I think I'll get back to that in the following video.
They're called: "if...", "ifdef", "ifndef", "endif" & "elif".
Let me use an example, it'll be better.
Here I have my main.c
and I'm gonna do a "#" ...
You've seen "defines", we're gonna use that
I'm gonna use "ifdef".
If there exists a "define" of, let's say, "TOTO", then I'm going to do things...
For example, my main will be written.
Otherwise,
if "TOTO" hasn't been defined, The main won't even show.
Basically, "ifdef" means : if "TOTO" is defined, whatever is between # and endif
will be added to the file. Otherwise, it won't be.
So, here, has "TOTO" been defined? No.
As is hasn't been defined, if I do : "cpp main.c",
There's nothing anymore.
Same thing the other way round: "ifndef"
it means: if "TOTO" has not been defined, then, whatever's between #ifndef
and the corresponding endif, should be displayed onscreen.
This time my main came back.
We could assemble them. For example we could do:
if "ifndef TITI"
and add another "endif" here.
That would mean that if "TOTO" hasn't been defined,
we'll display what's between this "endif" and this "ifndef".
and if "TITI" hasn't been defined,
it'll display only what's between this "ifndef" and this "endif".
So normally, my main should appear.
Because neither TOTO nor TITI have been defined.
Let's see.
The main has reappeared !
Now, in order to define "TOTO", we've seen defines,
I told you we could use them as macros
but we could also just use them to define "TOTO".
If I write this... It's valid.
It means "TOTO" won't be replaced by anything. That's okay.
but for the preprocessor, "TOTO" is something that exists.
So, normally...
Again, "ifndef" means that "TOTO" hasn't been defined.
as we've now defined it, my main's disappeared.
Along with "ifndef' and "ifdef", you also have "elif",
"elif" = "else if"
But my advice is to avoid those and rather do blocks with "ifdef" and "ifndef",
it'd be easier.
With this, you'll be able to protect your files.h
and that's what we'll see in the next video.