Hello,
In this video, I'm going to talk about a new keyword, called "union".
unions look a lot like structures,
except that structures use to add data,
one after the other.
When we did a points structure, earlier, as I showed you in another video,
where I had 2 ints next to each other,
This time, unions will allow us to access the memory areas,
but in several different ways.
Again, the best way for me to explain this
is to show you.
So, I've got a structure s_test, which has
an int "i", a char "c", a float "f", and a char "tab[4]",
Let's create the union.
The same way we'd create a structure.
Union
Let's call our union,
u_test.
Semi-colon at the end.
I'm going to do the same thing inside.
You'll see, it'll be useful.
As I've told you, the difference
between unions and structures, is that
structures add elements one after another,
and the union will allow us to access
the same memory area, in many different ways.
For example, if I use the keyword sizeof,
which will give us the size of an element,
so for example the size of my structure s_test.
Here we go. Let's display it.
Here, we notice my structure is 16 byte.
Let's check. An int = 4 bytes,
a char is one byte, so that makes it 5,
a float is 4 bytes, so we have 9.
and a char tab[4], so 4 more bytes.
That makes 13 bytes. Not 16...
But why?
It's quite simple:
My compiler does some padding between my char and the float,
because in order to access memory faster,
basically the compiler will position the elements,
at addresses that are multiples of 4,
as the processor is "32 bits",
it'll create access on 4,
if we had a 64 bits processor,
it'd have created access on 8...
and therefore padding on 8.
I'm gonna prove it to you.
If I set a char xx[3] here,
recompile, and relaunch. Still 16.
Now, if I moved this char,
and then added it bellow the float,
well with this, we'd get 20.
Why?
Simply because there's been an extra padding of 1
So, in the end, my char[3],
meaning that with 3 bytes, there's a padding of 4.
So the size of my structure,
is the sum of all the elements
to which we add the padding.
Now let's use Union,
and you'll see how it changes every thing.
I'm gonna use my sizeof on my union.
here,
it indicates a size of 4.
Actually it takes the size of the biggest element.
An int is 4, a chat is 1, a float is 4,
and a char tab[4] is 4.
If I replaced it with tab[10],
just for fun,
we'd be at 12.
Once again: padding (google it)
I'll put it back to 4.
Let me show you how it works.
Let's create a new object of type "union"
so "union u_test",
which we'll call "a"
and indicate that if "a.i = 42"
Let's use a bigger number than 42...
how about 424242,
It'll be clearer.
My idea...
is to first display "a.i"
to show you its value is indeed 424242.
Here we go.
Now, let's try accessing my int, going through my tab,
and using each char from my char tab[4].
as a piece of my int,
(remember: 1 int = 4 bytes)
Normally, if I display:
char tab[0], tab[1], tab[2], tab[3]
I should access different parts of my int.
Here we go. Let's start over.
I'm going to add something to separate them.
To make it clearer.
At least you'll see better.
We can see 50, 121, 6 and 0.
Those are the 4 bytes my int is made of.
We could even do the math,
using "bc".
50 remains 50,
+ 121 x 256
because the first byte
is multiplied by 256 to the power of 0.
the 2nd byte, 256 256 to the power of 1,
the 3rd byte, 256 to the power of 2,
the 4th byte, 256 to the power of 3;
So : + 6 x 256 x 256
and normally,
we get the value of origin.
You get it.
Union allows us to access a memory area
in many different ways.
There are many advantages to this.
Up to you to figure out the rest.
In the meantime, I hope your day won't be too tough.
We've seen about everything there was to see today.