Hello,
In this video, I'm going to talk about a new keyword
something we haven't seen yet : "enum".
Be careful, enums are something a bit particular.
It'll allow you to set words instead of having numbers...
Enums are a bit like ints, actually,
but we generally use those to make lists.
it helps you know where you stand in your code.
for example, if you have values that
mean certain things such as error 1, error 2, error 3,
one of them is a segfault, the other is ... I don't know...
You need to name errors, and generally to do so, you'll use "enum",
to avoid having to use defines, one on top of each other, etc...
Or you're not sure you haven't used the same define twice,
with the same number.
So that's something that happens during compiling,
and that will allow you to generate a set of digits, you'll see.
I think an example would be quite appropriate, here,
Declaring enums is a bit like declaring structures...
You have to write "enum" followed by its name,
let's call it e_list.
Always followed by a semi-colon, because it's something that happens during
compiling, so we need to define what we're doing.
Just like structures, we can write "enum e_list"
and say it exists, but that's not very interesting, you'll see.
And here's how it works.
I'm going to devine a value 1, a value 2, a value 3, etc...
So let's call them val1, with a comma, val2, with a comma, val3, etc...
Now I can create objects of type e_list, exactly like structures,
and I have my variable "a" of type e_list.
And I'm gonna give "a" the value "val1".
Now, that's the one 'crappy' thing about enums in C...
all of a sudden, val1, which was part of the enum e__list,
but now it's become some sort of keyword.
Meaning val1 is worth 0, val2 is worth 1, and val3 is worth 2.
Basically it increases numbers, from 0.
For example, you could write that val1 is worth 4,
and then val2 will be worth 5, and val3, is 6.
You could also write that val1 is worth 4, val2 is worth 7, and therefore
val3 should be worth 8... Normally...
Let's check it out. So here, if I write val3...
and here, the value of my main's return.
I'm going to use a small trick to avoid having to show you functions.
First, let's see if it compiles.
It does. Let's execute "a" and then I'll do an " echo$? "
to get the last executable's return value,
and here we can see that it's 8. So val3 is indeed worth 8.
So that's about all you need to know about enums...
Normally you shouldn't be able to set the same value twice...
For example if you say : "val1 = 7" and "val3 = 7",
I think you're going to have a problem, but I'm not so sure...
Because it could let you do it...
Depending on versions, it let's you set the values you want...
The advantage is that it'll just keep listing...
As soon as you add a variable, it'll increase by 1 each time.
And that's the true advantage of enums.
Careful! The issue with enums is that all the names you're going to use here,
become names usable without having to write e__list before them.
So it's risky, dangerous, but there are cases in which that's exploitable.
Usually, when people set variable names, like this, for their enums,
they have fun re-adding their enums' names in front of their variable names.
So, for example, we could write : e__list val1, etc...
As simple as this. We could also add typedefs before,
if you want, but that's not very useful...
Because this e__list, I just used it to declare "a'.
But I could have used an int, it would've been the same.
Be careful, if you have 2 different enums,
and try and add them together,
certain compilation options will cause
errors, just to show you there's a
difference between both enums.