Hello,
Now that we're done with preprocessors,
let's move on to other keywords in C we haven't seen yet,
such as "typedef".
"typedef" is a keyword that allows us to redefine a type.
Meaning, you can create your own type.
There are huge differences with the macro "define",
which allows you to do a replacement, word by word,
whereas "typedef" really is for creating a new type.
And I'm going to show you those differences between "typedef" and "define"
How do we create a "typedef"?
Well, it's simple: "typedef" + type of base we want to transform.
for example, let's say I want my "int" to be called "cacahuete" ("peanut"),
As it's not a preprocessor word, it's really something that's executable.
So we have to add " ; " at the end.
That's important.
Now that I've done this, underneath my code I can write "cacahuete",
the variable "a", for example,
and then "a = 10".
And normally there shouldn't be any error during compilation.
For the moment, you can't really see a difference with "define"
except that it's in reverse,
meaning that "cacahuete" was on the left, and on the right was what's to be replaced
The real difference is during compilation.
The preprocessor will take care of it.
which requires other things.
meaning "typedef" also is subject to the scope.
What is meant by "typedef is subject to the scope"?
It means that, depending on where I put my "typedef",
It'll only affect an area.
For example, here, "typedef" only affects the main.
Let me show you. I'm going to create a new function as an example.
"void ft_fct(void)" and declare a new variable "cacahuete",
which I'm gonna call "a".
And I'm gonna do the same thing underneath: "a = 10".
Normally, this should not compile.
Here we go. There's a problem in ft_fct.
I have "cacahuete undeclared", because it has been declared beneath, here.
As I was saying, it's subjected to the scope.
If I added the typedef all the way at the top, out of the scope,
It doesn't respect the Standard, but that's OK.
It compiles.
That's the first big difference.
The second difference is something we could not do with a "define"
unfortunately it doesn't respect the Standard,
but I'll show you just to be exhaustive.
Imagine I write "int *", and call it "int_p".
Now. I have a new type of variable "int_p" which is a "int * "
Had I written this...
you'll see ...
had I written "int* a, b, c".
The asterisk is in the wrong place.
That's why we have to put it on the right, you'll see even better.
Here we can see that only "a" will be a pointer to int.
"b" and "c" are ints.
When we write this, here's what happens
Had I done a #define, let's call it "INTP",
it'd be replaced by "int * "
so had I written "INTP",
That's actually the same thing,
the asterisk, instead of being on the left, it'll be on the right.
because it's a word-by-word replacement, so my "a" would be a "int * "
but my "b" and my "c" would be ints.
However, with "typedef", if I wrote "int_p",
this time, "a", "b" and "c" would be pointers to int.
You probably don't see the point yet...
but there are many points to this.
The most blatant point, is the last one I'll show you, actually.
Going back to write()'s man, which we've already seen, with includes, etc...
Here, you see that write() takes a "size_t",
and returns a "ssize_t".
Those are typedefs.
Meaning that if one day, the person who created write() wants to modify
its data type,
by adding "include unistd", you have the "typedef" of "size_t",
and if tomorrow they want "size_t" to go from being an "unsigned int",
to becoming a "long unsigned int", they'd only need to change it in one place.
and if you've used "size_t" in your code, they'll also become "long unsigned ints"
The advantage is that it really performs a thorough check during compilation,
and it also tells us the names,
and not "int", because it's not a word-by-word replacement,
it's a "typedef int cacahuete",
and behind, it'll inform you about errors with a variable of type "cacahuete".
It also allows you to find things more easily.
That's it for "typedef".