So far, you've always compiled
your C sources using GCC
from your terminal.
You were writing lines like : "gcc [source file name].c",
in this case: source.c
which compiled your program
to an executable called "a.out".
We've seen that we could also, queue files,
when we have multiple sources,
or use *.c to compile them all
and generate the same a.out.
Perhaps some of you use the option "-o"
to specify a program's name,
here, for example, "-o awesomeprog" which is created from source.c
and now we have our executable "awesomeprog"
which is next to our previous executable "a.out".
What you need to understand is that GCC is a complex compiler
and you must take the time to really understand how it works
and get to know its options.
The sooner you'll do this, the sooner you'll be comfortable with the compiler
and able to fully take advantage of it.
Gradually, as you learn how to use GCC,
you'll realize that this compiler
has very complex options, and sometimes,
if we want to use separate compilation,
or set tasks before and after compilation,
or add "include" directories, or libraries... Who knows!
compilation lines in the terminal can become really complicated.
And soon, we realise that we're gonna need a Shell script to organise it all.
In the first part of this course
we'll discover a new tool called Makefile
which will allow us to solve this problem efficiently,
and do exactly what we want.