Now that you know how to define rules for your Makefile,
Let's discover together how to use those variables.
We're quickly going to see that certain names will be ccomplex
to write, will have to be dynamic, or will be created
from something else.
So it'll be very practical to be able to regroup
these complicated expressions in a variable,
and then reuse it in your Makefile.
The syntax, for variables, is very simple:
You just write the name of the variable,
followed by the "=" sign, then the definition of this variable.
For example, here, the string
"42 is for the braves".
Please excuse my accent.
And now, I have the possibility
to refer to my variable TEXT in my Makefile,
which will be replaced by "42 is for the braves".
Notice how I chose to use capital letters for my variable?
It's a norm I'll ask you to respect as well.
In the Makefile, your variables are in capital letters.
Once we have this variable, we're going to want to use it.
For example, I'm going to define a regle_a ("rule_a")
which will use the variable TEXT.
For this, the syntax is a little special,
we're going to use "$" and then the name of the variable
we want to refer to, in parenthesis.
This way, by reading regle_a, the command "make" will know it has to replace
"$(TEXT)" by "42 is for the braves".
Let's test this together.
I advise you to add a shortcut for "make",
know that if you invoke "make"
without arguments, the first rule encountered in your Makefile,
will be the one used.
It's a practical behavior to use your
default compilation rule.
In my example's case, the first rule of my
Makefile being regle_a, if I invoke "make" without parameters,
this regle_a is the one that'll be executed.
Proof : "echo" of my variable TEXT has been replaced by
the string "42 is for the braves".
We can see that the display of the line below, corresponds well.
Evidently, we can do much more complex things with
Makefile's variables.
You'll see that we can generate data, but that's something
I'll let you discover on your own.
There are hundreds of tutorials on the Internet,
which will teach you the basics of variables.
See you in a moment for the rest of the lesson.
We'll look at a more complete example of Makefile.