The syntax for declaring a pointer to function variable,
may seem a little overwhelming at first, because it's really different
from everything we've seen so far.
Here, I left the declaration of a variable of type int, the declaration
of a pointer to int, and, for your information,
I'm also going to write the syntax to declare a function
which will inspire us for the syntax of a pointer to function declaration
Remember, this is how we write a prototype
For example, "void f",
parameters between parenthesis, for example, char c.
Here, we've declared a function that returns nothing, so "void",
which is called "f", and which takes a character as a parameter, called "c".
In order to declare a pointer to function,
we're going to use a similar syntax, but with a subtle difference.
The syntax you're gonna use is as follows:
to declare a pointer to function which doesn't return anything,
so VOID, and that takes a character as a parameter,
we'd write :
void, then between parenthesis, "*" and the name of our pointer to function,
for example "funptr", and then
the parameters we want, so here a "char".
Notice how I didn't specify a name for my parameter's variable?
I could have named it, but I won't,
because for pointers to functions,
we can skip naming them.
What you need to notice, is that
I've set my pointer to function name between parenthesis,
and put an asterisk before it.
Let me show you a more complete example,
which we'll compile,
to see how it works.
I'm going to declare a variable of type pointer to function,
which I'll call "f", and which will take
a random char as a parameter.
Then I'm going to assign a function's address
to my pointer to function.
Here, I'm going to use the address of my function ft_putchar(),
which is defined just above.
Then I'll be able to call my function ft_putchar()
by using my pointer to function "f".
The syntax is the same as for a function call.
"f", open parenthesis, pass a parameter, for example the character "z",
close my parenthesis and add my semi-colon.
Now we'll be able to compile.
Looks like it compiled...
and here's my executable "a.out".
If I execute it, the character "z" is being displayed.
Note that, as pointers to functions have a syntax that can be quite tricky,
there's always the possibility to do a Typedef on their type,
to make them easier to use.
The syntax for a Typedef is as follows:
I'm going to make an alias of the type's name, instead of the variable,
as if I used this syntax
to declare my pointer to function.
I'm going to call it "funptr"
And pass it a parameter "char", for example, and add the semi-colon.
I can now use my Typedef as a type,
so I'll be able to use "funptr"
and call my variable, for example, "f",
for it to work.
Compiling....
Executing...
And the result is exactly the same.
See you in the next video, for the last part of today's lesson,
where I'll add some extra info
on pointers to function. I'll also show you examples
that are more extensive.