Hello everyone, and welcome to this lesson
about pointers to function.
Recently, you've discovered the notion of pointers, and
you've used it to store variables, addresses,
Let's go back over it quickly, to make sure we know
what we're talking about.
Remember we could, for example, declare a variable,
in the following manner: "int x", which will define a variable of type int,
called "x".
We've also seen that we could declare variables with
another variable's address as a type : with pointers.
A variable that has an int's address.
For example, "y" would be declared as follows:
So here, we have a variable "x" of type "int", and a pointer to int "y".
We had the possibility to give a value to "x",
for example "42", and then reference the address of "x" in "y",
by writing "y = &x" (the address of "x").
Those are syntaxes you know well.
And you get the idea.
Now that we have the address of "x" in our "y",
we'll be able to use the value of "x", by using "y".
For this, we have to dereference "y" with the operator " * ", which is
the dereferencing operator, and assign a new value to "x".
For example, 0.
So here, "y"'s content (the dereferenced address of "x"),
is worth 0, and not 42 anymore.
Today we'll discover that we can reference the address of a function,
in a pointer.
That's what we call pointers to functions.
See you in a moment to discover the syntax for these
pointers to functions.