Now that we know the syntax and the simple semantics of Makefiles,
we're going to be able to put all of this in action,
and create a first real Makefile
which will do something,
like compile your program.
Let's define a certain number of variables, and rules,
which will be rather standard.
But I'd like to insist on something very important,
it's that this Makefile is not meant to be complete, accurate,
or enough to submit your project.
What I'm showing you are merely examples,
like an initiation to the problematics,
they're not answers.
So if you submit this Makefile, you'll have problems,
you'll see it's full of errors, that there are things
that it can't do, and it's up to you to figure it out for yourselves
by reading documentation, etc..
Take this code for what it's worth, it's just an average example
of a Makefile's possibilities, to compile a program.
I've started by defining a variable I've called NAME.
it'll take for value, the executable name
I'm trying to generate.
It's a rule, I called it NAME, but you could call it TARGET,
or TOTO if you wanted to.
However, NAME seems like a reasonable name to me, so I'll advise
you to use it.
Below, I defined a 2nd variable called SRC,
which will gather all C sources I want to compile.
So in this case, I'm targeting the file "source.c" which is
in my current directory, but I could add as many as I needed.
If you need more lines to add your sources,
you'll need to jump lines with "\", the same way used for
preprocessor macros in C.
Here, I only have one source file, so we don't have to do it.
Below, I have 5 rules that are pretty standard for a Makefile :
ALL (rule that takes the same name as the target program),
CLEAN, FCLEAN and RE.
We know that if we invoke "make" without arguments, it's the 1st
rule encountered in my Makefile that'll be executed. So here it's ALL.
This convention will allow you to
call the rule that'll launch the compilation.
This rule is the rule NAME, or actually the value that'll be taken
from the variable NAME.
So in our example, we're talking about "awesomeprog".
So, this rule NAME, is the rule that will
launch compiling, by calling GCC with the option "-o",
to specify the executable name to be generated,
and I'm going to use my variable $(NAME) to specify that name.
Then I'll list the sources I wish to compile,
for this, I use my variable $(SRC),
which I've defined just above.
The 3 rules below are utilitarian rules
to help with the project.
The 1st is the rule CLEAN, which will just clean by removing
all object files (.o) generated during compiling.
You'll have the possibility to use this rule
to erase other useless files,
for example, files that have "~" in your Shell.
Here, I chose not to do it, but you definitely should.
The 2nd rule is FCLEAN,
which is a lot like CLEAN, and that's why
it'll call CLEAN - which it depends on -
every time I call FCLEAN, CLEAN will be called first.
This rule adds the deletion of the generated executable.
What's it good for?
If I compile my program, I get files.o and my executable.
if I call CLEAN, it'll remove all the files.o,
but keep my executable. If I call FCLEAN, I'm going to
clean up all files.o and also delete the executable.
The last of these utilitarian rules, is the rule "RE" which allows
a reset of the compilation, meaning starting all over again
in a clean environment.
For this I first have a call to the FCLEAN rule which it depends on,
then a call to the rule ALL.
Basically, when I call the rule RE,
first, everything will get cleaned up, and then my program
will be compiled again.
Let's use this Makefile together.
In my directory, I have a file source.c and my Makefile.
If I call MAKE, the default rule that will be called
will be my first, so ALL, which calls the rule $(NAME),
which is going to compile my program with
gcc -o awesomeprog source.c.
Notice how the variables "NAME" and "SRC"
have, respectively, been replaced by their values.
I also have the opportunity to try CLEAN.
As I didn't get any files.o during this compiling,
it's kind of useless, but it'll rarely be the case.
If I want to clean some more and remove the executable,
I can call FCLEAN,
which will clean up my directory by removing not only files.o, but also
the generated executable.
And if I want to start over and clean everything up and recompile,
I'll call MAKE RE.
Here we can see everything's been cleaned up / erased,
and then everything's been recompiled.
So in my directory, I have an executable that's ready.
I think we've gone through the basics of Makefiles.
That should get you started.
As I've said many times,
this lesson is just a preview. It's not meant to give you
all of the answers. Just the notions.
You'd better go check what the Internet
has to offer.
You'll come across many tutorials, and articles on the subject,
and you'll be able to make your own Makefiles.
You'll see we can do a lot of interesting things with Makefiles,
Such as making sure your
compiling doesn't just generate some
files.o and link them to an executable,
but instead, something more complex, with directories, copies, links,
and everything that's necessary to
compile a real program.
On these words, I'll leave you to your exercises.
Good luck!