Hello
and welcome to D11 of C bootcamp.
Today we'll learn an important concept:
chained lists.
Chained lists are, to put it simply,
a group of links dispersed in memory
but interconnected, forming a chain.
These links, basically structures,
contain some data
and, a characteristic
that I'd like to highlight,
a link or a pointer to the next element/structure in our list.
Thus, adding or deleting an element
or even changing your list's order
is easy and only requires you
to be comfortable with pointers.
Unlike arrays,
When you want to add an element to an array,
you have to allocate a larger memory area
than the one needed for the first array
then you have to copy all of your first array’s elements
and finally to free the first array
then add all the elements you want and then free your first array.
Even if it doesn't cause problems when you manipulate a small amount of data,
malloc will have a hard time trying to find a contiguous area that's large enough
when you'll try to manipulate a bigger quantity of data.
Chained lists only need to be linked to the new element.