You have to understand that when we run operations on a File Descriptor,
and that one hasn't been closed, there's a sort of reading 'head'
that points to the ongoing byte.
Let's call the difference between the ongoing byte and the byte 0 : Offset.
So the first...
Let's use this example where I've described a few operations
on a File Descriptor, and the consequences of the Offset.
So now we have a README file of 42 bytes,
which we open without any particular flag.
The File Descriptor is 42.
The offset currently is at 0.
Let's read 12 byte from this FD.
This should take the Offset to 0 + 12.
Let's then read 30 bytes, which will give us an offset of 42.
Offset of 42, file of 42, we've therefore reached the end of the file.
Let's do a READ of a byte, which will return 0,
because we cannot go forward.
How could we move the head of reading
to another place in the file?
The last call system I'll show you
will answer this question.
It's called LSEEK.
LSEEK takes 3 parameters : 1) the file descriptor in question,
2) the offset of the result or calculation
3) the mode of calculation.
Have a look in it man, it's all explained there.
LSEEk returns the new offset, or -1 in case of error.
Let me show you an example of LSEEK usage.
Our offset is equal to 42.
Let's do an LSEEK of -40, with the SEEK_END mode, which means
we start from the end.
So, 42 - 40, LSEEK returns the offset 2, and we're back to the
second byte of the file.
Let me illustrate this with code.
I have my base of opening and reading of the file in "read only"
I'm simply going to add LSEEK here to go back 10 bytes.
The result won't be useful, It'll cause an infinite loop,
but it'll illustrate what i want, perfectly.
Compiling...
Launching, and, infinite loop, as expected.
LSEEK could be useful to reach the end of the file,
but it's useless, as Open already does it with the flag O_APPEND.
Moreover, re-reading data isn't very useful...
Even if that's what I just did.
This concludes today's lessons.
I strongly advise you to read the mans for different system calls,
and also, remember to alway check the returns of your syscalls,
especially for OPEN and READ.
Thank you.