Hi everyone
and welcome to this D12 of C bootcamp.
Today we'll learn how to manipulate files in C.
We'll see how to open a file,
close it, read from it
or write in it.
Let's start with
the concept of file descriptor (FD)
When you ask your system
to open a file
it returns a file descriptor.
A file descriptor is an integer.
The system keeps in memory some sort of table which associates every
file descriptor opened by a process with a file
When you get this file descriptor,
you can use it to manipulate the file.
Look at this example :
My program asks the system to open
the file named README, the system opens it
and returns the file descriptor 42.
Now, I can refer to FD 42
to manipulate this file
You have probably already used file descriptors
maybe without knowing it,
especially in the ft_putchar() function
which you must know very well by now.
This function allows you to
write your character in FD 1
If you read the man for "write"
you'll learn that the first parameter
is a file descriptor.
the file descriptor 1, which is part of a set
called standard file descriptors.
There are 3 standard file descriptors :
FD 0 or STDIN
which is your standard input
for example, when you type
on your keyboard in your shell,
you are using the standard input
FD 1 or STDOUT is the standard output
think of the characters displayed in your shell
like when you use putchar()
FD 2 or STDERR is the error output
which is also displayed in your shell.
This concludes the introduction,
in the next video,
we'll learn how to open and close a file.