In this first video, I'm going to
explain how to use
binary trees in their most simple form.
What's a binary tree?
It's a data structure which allows us
to store and organise elements
of any type, the same way a chained
list would.
Except that a chained list only has
one following element.
Here, you'll have two: right and left.
Let me show you how a tree looks
like schematically.
So this is a tree. Super pretty.
You can see that's it's organised
in a strange manner.
How is it sorted?
It's simple. For each node, you'll have
on the left, all elements that are
inferior to it,
on the right, all elements that are
superior or equal to it.
If I take any node to compare it to
another,
for example, 2 compared to 4.
4 > 2,
so it's on the right.
If I take 0, it's inferior to 2,
so it's on the left.
And if I take 1, it's smaller than 2,
but superior or equal to the other 1,
so it's in the right place.
That's how a binary tree is sorted.
What's the point of using binary trees,
when it comes to a list?
With the tree, the traversal
is much faster.
I'm going to transcribe my tree
into the shape of a list, like here.
See, same elements are sorted.
Imagine, for example, that I'm looking
for the 4. So the worst case scenario.
I'm gonna have to take one, two, three,
four, five, six paths.
So I have to do six jumps to
reach my 4.
Whereas in my tree, I do one... two...
three.
So half as many.
This allows us to go faster.
And it'll be very useful when you'll
have to store
a large amount of data.
That's actually what databases
use to store multiple
elements together.
Another case of binary tree usage,
is with certain types of parsers.
You'll learn about that later, it's
not today's topic.
It allows us to store other things,
such as tokens.
What does a binary tree look like in C?
It looks like this.
Here we have the complicated shape
of the binary tree.
Considering we have a parent, too.
So we have a structure s_btree,
which is a node from the tree.
It has a parent, the equivalent of
"previous" in a double chained list,
and has two children: right and left.
And then data, to store data.
How to traverse a tree?
You've seen it is weirdly sorted.
There are many techniques, depending
on what you want to do with them.
Let me show you the diagram.
The first type of traversal is the
Depth-first order traversal,
meaning we'll retrieve the sorted
elements in the fist case,
knowing there are different
variations.
The most common type of traversal is :
I'm scanning through the right,
I'm scanning myself,
I'm scanning through the left,
Or the other way around:
left-me-right.
If we base our example on this tree,
I'm starting on the first node,
I'm going to the left, and again,
Here I don't have a left side nor a
right side, so I'll display myself (0).
Going back up, displaying myself (1),
going to the right (1),
going back up, displaying myself (2),
going to the right
(3, as there's nothing on the left) and
then I go back to the right and display 4.
That's in-order traversal.
There's also the pre-order traversal,
which looks like in-order traversal,
exept here, we display before.
It'd look like this:
2-1-0-1-3-4.
In the post-order traversal, we display
after, but we're not
going to do them all.
The second case of traversal is
the Breadth-first traversal.
In this case, I'll read it myself.
Then I'll read my children,
then my children's children...
by level.
I'd get something like this:
2-1-3-0-1-4.
It's a little different.
A little more complicated
to implement in C.
In the case of an in-depth traversal,
we use a DFS.
Google it.
For the breath-first traversal,
we use a BFS,
You can google it too, if you're curious.
So, that's how you do traversal.
One of binary trees' disadvantage
compared to lists,
is that the insertion is more complicated.
Here, if you want to add elements,
it's a bit tricky,
so we use what's called dichotomy.
It consists of testing a value,
e.g.: the first one you
come across in the tree.
Let's say you want to insert -1.
Here, you'll check whether -1 is smaller.
It is.
So you go on the left.
Check if -1 is still smaller.
It is.
Going on the left.
It's the case here too, so you'll
add a -1 here.
So it'll be the left child of 0.
Now let's imagine you want to add
a 1, or another 0.
You'll check if 0 is smaller than 2.
Yes. So you're gonna go on the 1,
check if 0 is smaller than 1. Yes.
You go here.
Here, it's superior or equal, so
you'll add it on the right.
And you've just done an insertion
in a tree.
This type of binary tree isn't necessarily
adapted to all cases.
Imagine I inserted all my elements in
a certain order, and end up
with something like this.
I've inserted 10, then 9, then 8, then 7,
then 6.
My 10 has an element on the left,
but none on the right.
Same for the 9, etc... to infinity.
It looks more like a comb than a tree.
So we look the speed, and waste memory
by having 2 nodes every time, when we only
use one.
In the next video, I'll show you
how to solve this problem.