Hello and welcome to this first day of C : day 02.
I'm going to show you how to write your first program in C,
and how to compile it so that it can be executed by the machine.
First, let's open the file "jour02.c" with emacs
The ".c" extension lets us (and the machine) know it's a source file.
As soon as you open (or create) a file.c with emacs,
use Ctrl-C and Ctrl-H to generate the school Header.
If you're using vim, you'll have to use Fn-F1.
We'll start by declaring our program's entry point with the function main().
In C, all functions have a type (int, char, etc..)
they return a value of that type whenever they are used.
So here we're going to create the main() function, which returns an int.
If your function doesn't return anything, you'll have to write "void" (= null).
No variable means nothing to return.
As our function main() returns an int, let's write the return right now.
Assuming there was no error in our code, we'll use the default return code:
return(0) The "0" indicates everything went well.
Normally, main() takes arguments, but for your first program, we won't.
Here we go. We created a function that does nothing but return 0.
Just saying "everything went fine".
Let's save our file with Ctrl-X Ctrl-S,
with Ctrl-Z, emacs will run in the background.
You can see in the Shell that the task was suspended.
Now, let's compile our file with gcc, which is the compiler.
gcc has several options,
for instance -o which allows us to define the type of gcc output file,
meaning the name of the executable we've created.
So let's create an executable called "jour02", using the source file "jour02.c"
Be careful not to mix them up, otherwise you'll overwrite "jour02.c"
There we go! gcc has created our file.
See in our directory we now have 2 files : "jour02" and "jour02.c"
We now have the executable (see files' access rights)
to make sure we're executing it in the current directory, we'll use "./"
before our executable's name.
That launches our program, but as it doesn't do anything, there's no output.
So let's make it do something.
With "fg" (foreground) we reopen emacs.
Let's use a basic system call : write().
So, if you remember (or not), we'll use write() on the standard output,
which is the File Descriptor (1)
We'll just display one character, for instance "@",
and specify how many characters we want to display from this string,
so here, just one.
Let's quickly check out write()'s man, we can do this simply by doing Meta-X man...
... we'll look at the man 2 write(). write() is a system call.
mans are indexed by type, and man 2 is about system calls.
so we want to type "man 2 write".
It splits our window into two. To switch windows, just do Ctrl-X-O.
As you can see, write() requires the header "#include "
so that the compiler has the declaration and knows what arguments are required
and what the output parameter is.
So let's add this header.
Stil Ctrl-X-O to switch windows.
We can see that write() requires a file descriptor,
- The (1) that represents our program's standard output -
a buffer - which is a string. In our case just "@",
and a size - number of bites to be displayed -
Save your modifications (Ctrl-X, Ctrl-S), suspend emacs (Ctrl-Z)
Re-compile.
Everything went fine.
Launch your program. "@" is being displayed on-screen.
Why is there a "%" at the end ?
Because there's no carriage return in our program.
So let's add one ("\n") and change the size of our string to 2 characters.
Re-compiling, re-launching...
That's better!
Now that we're created our first function, let's move it to a sub-function,
which we'll call ft_putchar(),
which will also return an int.
So, ft_putchar() will take a "char c" and we'll simply take the write()
from the main() and move it up.
Cut the line with Ctrl-K. Do it twice to get the carriage return too
Paste with Ctrl-Y
and in our sub-function we'll be able to write the character...
... It's a little complicated,...
with the ampersand "&" we give a character's address,
instead of the character itself,
which allows us to transform it into a string (char *)
Here, we can either return(0), which means everything went well,
either change the function's type to void (returns nothing). Let's use return(0).
We're going to use our function ft_putchar()
and this time we'll use simple quotes because it's a character, not a string.
We're going to do a second time for the "\n".
Let's close the man window with Ctrl-X-1.
As you can see, our program will start its execution from the main()
The main() calls the sub-function ft_putchar().
ft_putchar() displays what we put as parameter in the "char c".
It returns, then we're back to the point of execution at the end of this function.
Then we carry on.
And then we end up with a ft_putchar() of a line-break ("\n").
in this case, write(1 ... ), the "char c" becomes "\n",
it's one character, so 1. We return, and we're done.
Let's test this. Ctrl-X Ctrl-S save our program.
Re-compiling
launching
It did what we wanted.
Now. Let's try something a little more complex.
Let's create a function that displays N-times the character passed as argument.
Let's call it ft_nputchar().
So we need the character we want to be displayed,
and an int(n) for the number of times we want that character displayed.
Here, we'll simply use this int(n) to count.
We could modify it the hard way, but let's try and keep it simple for now.
We need a counter "i", which will start from 0.
And we're going to add a loop with while() - while (i) is smaller than (n) ...
while (i < n)  ,
we'll display the character -
by calling our ft_putchar() function
and as long as it's lower than (n), we'll increase (i)
i = i + 1;
and once (i) is equal to (n), it'll stop.
So if we say that the argument (n) is equal to (1),
we start with (i), which equals to (0), therefore smaller than (1),
starting our first loop.
we increase (i) by (1). So (i) goes from (0) to (1).
The loop starts over again. As (i) isn't lower than (1), the expression is wrong,
so we exit our loop while() and return (0)
So we'll try the same thing... Here we'll call ft_nputchar(), and ask it to display
42 times the character "@" followed by a line-break.
Ctrl-Z, emacs runs in the background.
Re-compiling
Launching.
Okay. Let's check.
Normally we should have 43 characters, because the "\n" counts as a character too
Here we go. We have 43 characters!
With these simple examples, you should be able to write your own programs in C
Up to you to do the rest !
Cheers!