Hello.
In this video I'm going to teach you how to declare & assign a pointer to something
So, I've prepared a main, as you can see on the screen.
I've also prepared a couple of functions, which we'll talk about later.
I'm going to explain how to declare a pointer to int.
'Cause a pointer must point towards something, and you have to tell it
what kind of thing it should point to.
It's easier than it seems, you'll see.
So. I wanna do a pointer to int...
It's quite simple, just type "int", and then, stuck to our variable
- we could put the star on the left too, but to respect our school's Norm,
we have to put it on the right -
see what I just did? I've declared my pointer "ptr" to int.
The star means it's a pointer. And what does it point to?
It points to whatever's on the left - in this case, an int.
Now, I want to take a's address, and put it in "ptr".
As I've said earlier, a pointer contains an address.
Here it contains an int's address.
So before, when you wanted to declare a, and to set a's value to 3,
you'd type "a = 3;".
Now I'm going to declare "ptr" is equal to something...
and we're going to need the "&" sign, to retrieve the address of something...
Here I want to retrieve a's address. So " ptr = &a; "
So here I've basically written "ptr is equal to a's address".
So "ptr" contains a's address.
Everything's got an address in C. And I'm going to prove it to you shortly.
So let's display this onscreen...
I'm going to display ptr's value. I've created a little function just for that...
(look at the screen)
Here we go : This is a's address.
It's not its value. It's its address.
Which means I can change a's value, Ex: " a = 42; "
If I then re-display a's address, you'll see it won't have changed...
"a" is a memory slot,
and no matter how much I try to modify it, its address won't change.
See, it's the same thing displayed twice.
So. We've seen we could display an int's address with a pointer to int.
And now I'm going to purposely make a mistake.
And declare a "char", let's call it "c",
I'm going to give it a value, let's go with 'b',
And now I'm going to try and put c's address in ptr.
What's gonna happen ?!
Yup, I got an error message: "assignment from incompatible pointer type".
Which means I'm trying to put a character's address in a pointer to int...
They're not compatible. Won't work.
What I should have done to make it compatible
is declare a pointer to char instead of a pointer to int.
Here we go, that should do the trick. ptr has become a pointer to char.
Let's re-compile... It works.
So we've seen how we can dereference a variable, how to retrieve its address,
and assign it to a pointer.
In the next video I'll show you how to use this pointer to access a variable.