Hello!
In this video, I'm going to talk about something special.
There's a certain type of pointer,
you may have noticed it in my videos...
See here? There's "void *ptr".
That's weird, considering the meaning of the word void ...
You cannot declare an object of type "void".
However, you can declare an object of type "void *ptr".
You can add as many asterisks as you want,
but the logic changes.
What's a "void *ptr"?
It's a pointer to nothing.
In the end, it means it's a pointer to anything.
Let me show you with an example.
So here we have a main with an "a", a "ptr" and a "ptr2".
"a" has a value, and "ptr" = the address of "a",
"ptr2" = the address of "ptr". So far, so good.
That'll compile. "a" is an int,
"ptr" is a pointer to int, and it takes the address of "a",
"ptr2" is a pointer to pointer to int,
so it takes "ptr"s address. All good.
And now, I'm going to create a new object,
a "void *".
I'm going to call it "superptr".
And so "superptr", will take as a value,
the address of "ptr2".
For example...
And you'll see I'll manage to compile anyway.
No errors, no problem...
even though I've used compilation flags...
basically, as I've mentioned before
all pointers are addresses.
Inside the memory, they all have the same size.
Which means that the only difference between "ptr" and "ptr2",
happens during compilation...
in order to avoid errors,
we said that "ptr2" was a pointer to pointer to int
and "ptr" was a pointer to int. So if we mix them up,
and say that "ptr2" equals to "ptr" - although they're both addresses,
the compiler will tell us there's a problem and we've mixed them up
and that we shouldn't have.
Now... There's something that exists,
that may be of use, but you'll see that much later,
called "void *".
Basically, "void *",
their point is that they're just addresses
and they can take any pointer's address
but mostly they can return this address to anyone.
Normally.
See, for example,
I'm going to do something very dirty.
I'm going to write "ptr = superptr"
And if all goes well,
and if the compiler isn't too mean,
normally it should compile.
I don't know if you can see,
but I wrote that "superptr" equals to the address of "ptr2"
and then I made it so "ptr" contains the address of "ptr2"...
so "ptr" is a pointer to int, and "ptr2" is a pointer to pointer to int.
So yeah, there are many stupid things you can do with "void *"
What's great about "void *",
is that it can take any address,
which will be useful when writing generic functions.
But you'll see that much later.
So, for now, just know that a "void *" is a pointer on anything
and you can use it to pass a pointer's address to another pointer,
without knowing its type.
That's all you need to know.
But beware...
Okay, last notion for today.
If you do "superptr[1] = 12", just for giggles,
you'll see that we have a problem... Normally...
That's because we're trying to dereference a "void *"...
The problem being, as I've mentioned before,
"[1]" is like writing "*(something + 1)"
And that's a problem.
My compiler needs to know (when I do "+ 1")
the size of what I point to. And right now I'm pointing to "void"
So it doesn't know its size. And that's a problem.
So it refuses to do the "+ 1" I asked him to do.
and even if I hadn't done the "+ 1", had I just done this...
When I use the "*", it needs to load what I'm pointing to
in the memory.
But as it doesn't know the required size,
It's not a "char", it's not an "int"...
It doesn't know what it is...
Therefore it refuses to do this operation.
Conclusion : "void *" are just for transporting addresses.