Hello
Today's lesson will be about character string manipulation
What are they for ? And how to use them.
What's a character string ? It's an array of CHARs
Remember D03's lesson about arrays?
It's simply an array of type char
Let's declare our char array.
We're creating a main().
So the type is char. We need square brackets,
that's an array semantics.
Let's assign a value to our array : "Hello".
Basically, on the right, there's an exhaustive representation
of the memory.
How is our char-string stored?
We simply have, in box 0,
the character "H", in box 1, the character "e",
and so on.
Character strings have a particularity,
they have an exclusive way of ending themselves,
by using the special character "\0"
Soon you'll see why it's so useful.
Moving on from theory... to practice!
Let's create the function ft_putstr(). You've had to create this one
in previous Bootcamp days. So this is a gift ;-)
let's pass it the string,
and add another function : ft_putchar(),
so that we can have a line break ("\n") at the end of out program,
to make it clearer.
Let's start with the ft_putchar() function.
Which i'm sure you now know by heart.
I'm sure you also know everything about write() too,
so we won't expand on that.
write() of 1, with the address of c...
The heart of the matter: ft_putstr() takes our char-string as a parameter.
What does ft_putstr() do?
It iterates on each element in our table of chars
in order to display them.
How does it display ? It calls ft_putchar().
So we'll have a loop, and a stopping condition.
For each loop, a call to ft_putchar().
with...
our character string.
To use a loop means we need an index.
So let's initialise our index to 0.
and we'll use our index in the loop
in order to go through our string.
Finally, we'll increment our index.
We now need to figure out how to make it stop with a condition...
How can we know when a string has ended?
That's where the "\0" comes in and saves our lives!
We're simply...
going to stop as soon as we come across the first "\0".
Let's try and launch our program.
gcc test.c
./a.out
The string's displayed on the output.
So is the "\n".
Now let's get started with character string manipulation.
We've gone through our string,
now, let's change a value within our string.
Let's replace the first character
by a "Y".
So let's create a new function : replace_first_h_with_y().
Nothing exceptional about this function.
I'm sure it'll help you create much more useful functions for today's exercises
How do we get to our array's first box?
str[0], 1st box of our array, = 'y'.
Let's take a break, to check out what happens in the memory.
We're going to replace this "H", so the 1st box of our array,
by a "y".
That's the intended output...
so we're going to call our function
replace_first_h_with_y(str1).
and do some debugging just above,
to check if the replacement goes smoothly
gcc text.c
./a.out
"Hello", "yello". Perfect!
Let's create one last function for this lesson
that'll take 2 strings as parameters.
The 1st will be the source, the 2nd will be the destination,
and we're going to make a copy of the source's 1st character,
and add it to the destination.
I'm gonna start by declaring a second string,
str2[] = "yello".
Let's remove the previous function,
and create the function replace_first_char().
(resetting my array)
We have a second character string.
We're going to copy the 1st character (H) from our string src
into our second string dest
First character = src[0]
So dest[0] = src[0].
We just need to call our function replace_first_char(str1, str2).
And we'll display str1, then str2.
gcc ...
./a.out ...
"Hello", "Hello", "Hello".
Let's add debug lines, to see str2 before manipulation
"Hello", "yello", "Hello", "Hello".
So we've manipulated our string.
It doesn't have to be just the 1st box of our array...
we could do this for the 2nd box, or the 3rd...
It all depends on what you're trying to accomplish.
I hope that this lesson about string manipulation
will allow you to see clearer, and will help for today's exercises
which are mainly about loops and conditions
to be done when they're needed.
I hope this notion, which is quite simple,
and that will prove very useful today,
was clear.