Let's get started with Libraries !
I've prepared two files : ft_putchar.c and ft_putstr.c
I'm sure you all know what these do.
The syntax may be a little different,
but I'm sure you'll understand how I did it.
But that's not our main focus right now.
I'll simply get back to
creating a basic program.
So. You know that if I wanted to write :
"bonjour les gens" ("Hello people")
thanks to our ft_putstr(),
I should write a main() that calls this function.
And then compile.
We agree that if I only compile my main.c ,
the compiler's gonna have a go at me, and tell me:
"Thanks for calling ft_putstr(), but as I don't know where it is,
I can't do what you're asking."
So let's add ft_putstr.c.
And now, it tells me:
"I can't find the ft_putchar() you're calling in ft_putstr()..."
So let's add ft_putchar.c. And now it should compile.
And display my "Bonjour les gens".
I'm telling you all of this (again),
because, in order to create libraries, we'll first need to compile
the functions you want to put in it.
If I compile just my ft_putstr.c, it'll tell me that
there still isn't a ft_putchar(), but most importantly, we need a main()
in order to create an executable, as we've learnt earlier on in the Bootcamp
But I need to add my ft_putstr() to my library...
and I don't need my main().
For that, GCC has an option "-c".
Check the man for more info.
But look, it's created a ".o"
ft_putstr.o
It's an object. It's computer language.
As you can see...
if you try to display it, it's nonsensical.
Only your computer can read it.
But in order to do anything, we'll need a main.
As I said earlier.
In order to create a library,
we'll need .o files.
Just imagine your program is a wall...
and your .o file is a brick...
a brick that's ready, and that you'll be able to
place in more than one wall! In the sense that
once you've made your brick, you won't need to make it again.
and each time, you'll be able to use it everywhere.
That's actually quite practical. GCC knows how to do it.
we could simply just use our .o like this
meaning I can create all of my .o
(object files)
and create my binary thanks to those.
If I create this... It works very well. GCC successfully manages
to create a binary for me.
A binary that works.
GCC can do anything. We can give it those famous bricks,
and it'll know how to gather them, and provide us with our a.out.
We're not gonna need a main, we just want a library (lib)
that'll contain both our ft_putstr() and ft_putchar().
In order to do this, the first step is to create the .o files.
Once we have those .o we'll use a program called "ar",
with options "r" and "c".
I won't tell you what they do,
you can search the man.
Then, after "rc", we'll pass it our first argument,
our library's name. For example : libstr.a
Why libstr.a ? Because a library always starts by "lib".
I'll tell you why later on. So you add the name of your library,
here "str" and ".a" which is the extension
for static libraries.
There also exist dynamic libraries, but that's for another lesson.
So. libstr.a as my library's name,
then the files that contain the functions I want to add
to this library. So the two .o that I've just created.
And with these info,
AR does it's job, and displays libstr.a, with both my functions in it.
Now... How do we use it?
As I've mentioned earlier on,
I can take my main.c, and tell it that, the library
I want to use, actually is in the current directory.
By using the option -L, followed by a "."
I can tell it to look for my library in this directory.
and tell it the library's name it should look for : libstr.
Here, you should only indicate "lstr". That's how it works.
and that's why the name of the library
must start by "lib".
The "-lstr" will tell GCC that it's libstr.a I need.
Works the same as earlier,
when I compiled with my .c.
The benefit is that now, I can move my libstr.c anywhere.
I could very well move it into my nfs directory,
and link it from there.
This will allow you not to have to rewrite functions that you've
known from the beginning.
So that's one thing...
You've seen that "ar rc" was enough to create my library.
After a while, you'll realise that
there are a number of functions, which you'll create during this bootcamp,
that may be worth putting in your lib.
GCC successfully compiled with this command.
But the day you'll have over 3000 functions...
or even before... For example:
when you'll need ft_putstr, which is halfway through your lib,
it'll have to browse through your library in order to find
ft_putstr() and create your binary.
It won't use all of your library
to just use ft_putstr.
It's a time-consuming operation
and when you'll manage to create more complicated programs,
and need to use libraries, and that it'll have to search through
all of your libs to find the function in question,
GCC will take its time, because
it'll have to browse through them all.
For that, there's a program called "ranlib".
"ranlib" simply takes your library as a parameter,
and creates an index in your library
which will allow GCC to know where to go.
For example, it'll set ft_putchar() at position 1,
and ft_putstr() at position 2, (and so on...)
for all of the functions you may want to add to your library.
It's extremely practical, and optimises compilation time.
You'll see when you'll start collecting
a great deal of functions.
You should adopt this method ASAP. It'll prevent a great deal of bad surprises.
And it always works the same.
That's it for libraries.