Let's now see,
how to dynamically allocate memory.
Let's open a new file.c
The idea is to define, as a pointer,
a variable whose size hasn't been defined yet,
and that'll just contain the address of a memory area
that we'll ask the system to provide us with.
Let's declare a pointer: char* ;
more specifically, a variable str, that's a pointer of type char*.
So, we're defining a pointer. Not a fixed-sized string.
And we'll make this string's size vary.
In order to make it vary, we'll use
a "define", that we'll call "LEN", for example,
and define it to 42 bytes, for now.
So we're simply going to use
a "malloc" system call,
to which we'll pass the size
that we wish to allocate.
And then, we'll scan
this character string,
and fill it with random characters.
Fore example, we'll tell it
to display the '0' character,
increased by i % 10,
which will do 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9, and so on...
Now. Let me correct a few things...
First, we have to take care of the size
we pass to "malloc".
The idea is to ask a "malloc" of 42.
Our string has a size of 42,
we want a string made of 42 characters.
So we have to think about the "\0".
We'll add 1 to our malloc's size.
malloc expects a size in bytes.
we assume that 1 character = 1 byte...
just to be sure,
we're going to use the code "sizeof" :
for example, to do a sizeof of char,
which we'll multiply by the number of
characters we need.
A sizeof will give us the variable's size, in bytes.
For example, instead of having a string,
we'd like to have an array of ints.
We could do the same with int* str.
But that would mean that
here, we'd have to replace that by an int.
So to make it easier, we'll put *str
so that sizeof will simply take the same type as str.
It allows us to just change the type here,
and prevents us from having to change it everywhere in our code.
Let's have a look
at malloc's man.
To avoid warnings, errors,
or any other problem,
let's include the file defined here.
As it says in the man,
we can notice that
malloc's prototype
returns a void *
void * is an address without a type.
but str does have a type. So we're gonna have to cast it,
in order to give the type char* to what malloc returns.
So, we do have a type char* that corresponds to str...
malloc of the size of a character,
multiplied by the number of characters we want,
+ 1, for the "\0" we'll place here.
Here "i' is worth "LEN", so we're at the end of our string,
which we'll end with a "\0".
Once we've done all of this,
we're going to display our string.
Our string is displayed,
from 0 to 41.
Because the index starts at 0.
All 42 bytes are here.
We'll just add a line break.
It'll be prettier.
Let's now change our size, for example.
We'll set it to 21 instead of 42.
Recompiling...
Relaunching...
and our string's now 21 characters long, and the allocation worked fine.
We didn't even have to change anything in our code.
We could have done something like this...
But the problem here, is that
we allocate memory in a stable and definitive way.
With our method, we'll be able to
temporarily take memory,
and then free it.
So, let's remove the display,
because otherwise, it's going to cause problems,
and simply put a very long string,
of 42 million bytes.
So it's going to require 42 Mo of memory.
Or a little less, because 1Mo is 1024 * 1024.
So, we do the same, we allocate 42Mo,
we fill up our 42Mo,
we simply don't display them onscreen,
to avoid problems.
We'll just add something here,
to stop our program.
- we'll kill it, in the end, to get rid of it -
in order to check, with "top",
the memory used by our program.
We don't need ft_putstr anymore.
Let's relaunch our program in the background
so that we can see in "top" the memory used
It's in the background,
it's in its while(1), running.
Here it is, in "top",
and we can see it's using 40Mo of memory.
Let's let it run.
And now, going back to malloc's man,
we can see that there's another
system call : free.
Which will allow us to free memory,
previously allocated by malloc.
free takes malloc's " void * ",
and doesn't return anything.
It's still the same "define".
So what we're going to do,
before our while(),
is call free,
and pass it str,
which is the address malloc has returned a few lines before,
and compile this into a "a.out2".
Let's launch this "a.out2". Still in the background.
and now we can do a comparison in "top".
Our first "a.out" still has its 40 Mo of memory.
and "a.out2" has gone down to 132 Ko of memory.
We've freed the memory used by malloc
So this will allow us to perform
occasional memory allocations
E.g.: for work, or for chained lists,
or for things that don't have a size at first,
and to which we can't set a size
in the program... :
such as strings, arrays,
and chained lists.
That's it for malloc.