Hello again,
Let's keep going with #include,
but this time I'll explain the advantages of using files.h
to protect your functions, etc.
from prototype errors, etc.
Here's an example
I have a main that calls a function ft_fct
I added the prototype before.
This function takes an int as a parameter, and returns nothing.
This function doesn't do much.
It'll display "coucou" onscreen.
What I can show you, is :
Imagine you had a dozen files.c
which all called ft_fct.
You'd have to add the prototype each time.
So here, 1st advantage of #includes:
You'll be able to include this file,
everywhere.
You'll just have to do it once.
You'll then be able to change ft_fct's prototype
without having do rewrite it in 10 files,
you'll just write it in one single file
and it'll be re-copied during preprocessing,
before compilation,
And your new version of ft_fct will be here.
But mainly, it'll prevent other problems.
Let me show you with a simple example:
Imagine, imagine,
This was my function ft_fct,
I already added the include,
I'm going to remove it.
So, ft_fct took an int as a parameter,
I'm going to remove this too.
Doesn't take anything anymore.
So now my ft_fct doesn't take anything as a parameter.
Now, in my main,
no modifications,
I declare that ft_fct is going to take one parameter: an int.
So I send it a parameter.
And here, if I compile,
Here's what happens.
With ft_fct.c
It compiled.
It works.
Except that I'm doing something absurd
Because here,
I didn't pass anything as a parameter
Whereas in my main, I passed something.
We should've taken the problem in reverse...
ft_fct should have taken something as a parameter,
and I should've declared it didn't.
And in this case, it would've checked for infos on the stack
And we would've had a problem:
my code would've gone nuts.
So here, you see we can have difference
problems between files that really define functions,
and files that use them (where you've set a prototype)
The way to prevent this,
is to use includes.
So I've created a file fct.h.
which is local, hence why I'm using quotation marks
and it defines my function ft_fct
properly.
I'm going to include it into the ftc.c file to show you its benefits.
It's some sort of security.
I'm also going to include it in my main.c
So instead of writing the prototype, here,
I'm going to include it.
fct.h
And now, I'm gonna check
this ftc.h I've created.
So, here, we said
it took an int as a parameter.
So. My main,
no problem.
It does take an int as a parameter.
So let's compile and see what it does
And you'll see that,
considering there's a problem somewhere between the prototype and my function.
Now, it's up to me to decide...
in the end, ft_fct doesn't actually take any parameter,
So I tell myself
that actually, the function I created
doesn't take anything as a parameter anymore.
So I need to change it's prototype in fct.h.
I'm going to change it's prototype in fct.h.
So, here,
I'm going to pass it "void"
Here.
Recompiling
Once again,
I have another error.
But this time, the error isn't in fct.c anymore.
Now it's in the main.c.
Because, this time, my main,
as I've changed the prototype,
Well my main tells me that
Ah! I've tried to call it by passing it 10 as parameter.
and it doesn't work.
So here too, I'm gonna have
to remove the call with the parameter.
And this time,
It'll compile.
I can even show you...
If I do a CPP of main.c,
you see,
here we see
that we have our fct.h file
that's been re-written.
You can see the prototype written at the top.
Normally,
we'd like to avoid writing prototypes
at the beginning of every file.
But instead, use includes from here, now,
but most importantly,
don't forget to include the files.h in the corresponding files.c
So normally you should put your prototypes in files.h
and include them to their appropriate files.c
so that when you modify a function,
you'll know straight away during compilation.
And you'll be able to modify the files.h and files.c, accordingly.