Hello.
In today's first video,
we'll talk about a preprocessor command,
called "include".
We'll have to add an "#" before it,
because preprocessor commands usually start with #.
This command (include), allows you to include a file
within another file, BEFORE compilation.
So, during the preprocessing stage.
Let me know you how it works with an example.
Usually, you use the function write().
If you wanted to use it in your main(),
you had to write the prototype at the top.
To know which prototype to use for write()
you had to check its man page
and you'd see that write() takes an int, a const void *,
a size_t * (which is an unsigned int, you'll see that in a following video),
and a ssize_t, which is an int.
So if I wanted to use write(), I'd have to add its prototype
above my main().
In the man, it says "#include ".
That means that write()'s prototype already exists in a file.h,
called "unistd.h".
So instead of writing my prototype and compiling with it,
we'll use a grown-up technique, a real programmer technique,
we'll use includes.
So we write "#include", and then
The angle brackets mean we're getting this file from the PATH...
The PATH of the files that the compiler seeks.
You can specify this PATH, based on
the compiler's commands. Up to you to figure out how.
There also is another way that allows you
to include files in the present directory : "#include" followed by
the file's name in quotation marks
For example, I could include the file fct.h
What happens when I include unistd.h ?
You'll see. I'm going to try and compile with
-Wall -Wextra -Werror
No problem. No errors.
And here, I can indeed call my function write()
but let me show you what happened exactly.
The preprocessor command is called CPP.
It'll allow us to see what happens
before compilation.
Remember my main.c ?
I'll do a "cat" on it, so you can see.
Here. This was my main() with it's "#include"
Now, if I show you with CPP,
here's what's been added to it.
All of this, is the unistd.h file, which can include other files.
We can clearly see that.
See? There are many prototypes in it.
The prototype for write() is somewhere in there.
This allows us to use the write() function
without having to worry about its prototype.
This is incredibly useful, because every time unistd.h is updated,
depending on the distribution you're using,
you'll be able to include it, and you'll
have the correct prototype for write().
What you need to remember from this video,
is that when you do an "#include" of any file,
not necessarily a file.h,
you can include this file and its text directly,
before compiling,
without processing it.
And then, compilation can happen.