Hello,
In this video,
I'm going to talk about a new keyword: "struct".
"struct" is a keyword that will allow you to create groups of data,
which will be linked all together.
we call this a structure, actually.
and we'll see that in a moment, I'm going to show you an example.
Imagine we have a problem, and want to do
geometric calculations on ... points.
Imagine.
So imagine I have 10 points in an area.
One of the methods to define  10 points in a 2D area,
with variables, we'll use ints,
Let's not get crazy and use "floats".
So you'll have the choice to do this: "int x[10]" for example.
So those are the "x" coordinates of your 10 points.
and "int y[10]" are the "y" coordinates of your 10 points.
You'll always have to maintain your "x" and "y" together,
in parallel, and position yourself with both.
Okay, you probably think that it's a bit boring.
We could have, for example, done something called "point",
and here we'd have put 20.
and said that all odd numbers are "x", and all even numbers were "y",
or the other way round. Same thing.
So every time we wanted to access a point, we'd have to
access a value, the "+ 1" value, and then multiply each time by 2,
to access the following point. It's a bit hectic.
Let me teach you a way to move around more smoothly
between points, and how to define what a point is.
Those are called "struct". Because, to me, a point is 2 ints.
So how do we write it? We declare it: "struct".
And then, the name.
For example, let's call it "s_point".
We can declare a structure by doing this:
Here, you just say that it exists
It's a bit like functions' prototypes
There'll be a difference between declaring it and defining it.
I'm going to define it directly.
To define it, just like a function, I need curly brackets.
and end with a " ; "
So here, in my structure,
I'm going to define data, that my structure possesses once I've build one.
So for example, an "int x" and an "int y".
There.
So, based on this, I can, for example,
declare a new variable,
of type "struct s_point".
We'll have to write "struct" too, that's important.
The keyword ahead is important.
For those of you who know other languages where the "struct" disappears, be careful.
So the "struct s_point", let's call it "a", for example.
And now, if I wanted to modify the "x" of my structure "a",
Well, I'd have to write "a.x".
By adding that dot here, I can access the variable "x",
from my variable "a", which is a structure of type "s_point".
So now, in "x", I can put 10, for example.
and in "a.y" I could put 42.
In the long list of structures' advantages
for example, one of the advantages of structure,
is that, when you want to copy a dot into another,
you could do this...
And now, "b" is a copy of "a" (♫)
It means that if we modify "a", now,
"b" won't be affected. And vice versa.
So "b", now, it's "x" us worth 10 and it's "y" is worth 42.
So that's a huge advantage.
What out, when you do a function call, remember that we copy
So if you set a structure as a parameter, you'll get the exact same problem,
you'll have to copy - in this case - 2 ints, and risk doing heavy operations,
which would take up a lot of memory, having ginormous structures.
And is probably will happen.
So. In general...
we use pointers to structures, when we try and pass them...
except if you know what you're doing, in which case it's okay.
So, we've seen how to build structures.
And how to add data in them.
We can do what we want, we can even use "floats"
we can use chars, or other structures.
and add as many data inside as we want.
They just have to have different names.
Except for "x" and "y". Those can't have the same name.
See? It's just like normal variables.
Because otherwise, we don't know which fields you want to access.
So now, let me show you how to ...
The advantage of "typedef" with structures,
If you write this : "typedef struct s_point"
and then let's call this t_point;
What it does, is that instead of writing struct s_point, tabulation, variable's name
I'll just be able to write "t_point", and it'll be the exact same thing.
So here, you see that "typedef" helps save up lines.
Well, save up width. That's a small advantage.
Tess stuff to type.
Quite practical.
And I'm going to show you something else.
One last thing about structures.
So we've seen we could add data in those.
We've discovered a new operator : full-stop / dot.
There's a special rule for pointers...
Imagine I want to create a pointer called "ptr",
"ptr" takes the value of my structure's address (structure "a").
So, the thing is...
in order to access the element "x",
from "a", via "ptr",
In your minds, in all logic, we could've written this:
(*ptr), full.stop, "x".
Because basically, *ptr is the same as "a"
Had I written this... No problem, it works.
there's another way to write it. Using arrows.
The arrow can replace the asterisk-dot.
Meaning you're dereferencing your pointer.
And behind, you're going to look for a structure's element, because
the element towards which pointed your pointer, is a structure.
That's it, we've covered the basics of structures.
As simple as this. And with these basics, we'll be able to achieve many things.
It's a notion that we use a lot in C, so try and practice,
because you'll see, we're gonna use this notion a lot.