Hello
In this video, I'm going to show you
how to protect our files.h, with the preprocessor's help,
against multiple inclusions.
What's a multiple inclusion of files.h ?
You've just learnt about "include"
and I'm already showing you something that'll cause problems...
If you don't protect them,
you'll have problems with your files.h.
Here I have a main.c that I'm going to compile.
This main.c has an include of the file test1.h
Let me show you this test1.h file.
It's simply a #include of test2.h
test2.h, as you've probably guessed, will be test1.h's include.
So the preprocessor will try and do
inclusions, as many times as possible.
Surely you've realised that I've just created an infinite loop
and we're gonna have problems
Let me show you.
Here.
We have a problem.
How to avoid this?
Because maybe you sometimes want a file to include another.
You'll see, it's quite useful.
So how could we protect our files.h ?
And that's how we're gonna do it.
First, we're gonna start with something standard.
It's an #ifndef, if we haven't defined yet.
So we're gonna base our macro on our file's name.
Let's be good pupils
and respect the Standard.
So, __FT_, and name of my file in capital letters,
you should generally write your macros' names in capital letters.
_H__ at the end.
So, this means:
if,
if this macro hasn't been defined,
well, here, we're going to include this.
if it becomes "defined", then we'll stop including it.
You'll see that, normally, by doing this,
it shouldn't work yet. We're going to have to add something
Basically,
once I've gone in this "if" once, I'm making sure it don't go in it again.
Which means I have to make sure that this file.h is included only once.
A s simple as that.
If I go in it, it means that __FT_TEST1_H__ hasn't been defined yet.
So, when I go in it, I'm going to try and define it.
You'll see. __FT_TEST1_H__
And this, normally,
should make sure that test1 can be included only once.
Demonstration!
Normally, now...
it compiles.
If I do a "cpp main.c", here's what's gonna happen:
Remember that main.c includes test1.h.
and if you look,
test1.h,
well, here...
it included test2.h, which included test1.h, actually... but...
Oh, sorry...
this test1.h has just included test2.h.
test2.h attempted to include test1.h, but it was empty.
Here you go.
I'm gonna try and add some code, to make it clearer for you.
So, here, for example, I'm going to add a function's prototype.
A void. Let's call it "pouet1" {"honk1")
Just like this. You'll see better.
So, "puet1" is in "test1".
and in "test2",
I'm gonna add "pouet2"
See, I haven't protected "test2".
but that's okay, because "test1" will be included only once.
I'm sure of it, now.
I haven't protected test2 either.
Normally, you should protect all your files.h.
But that was just an example.
Let me show you what happens.
We can see that test1 has been included.
In the beginning, the first time we go in test1,
"ifndef" hasn't beed defined. Therefore we keep going down,
here we have the inclusion of "test2"
so we keep going down,
and we have the define of __FT_TEST, etc.
we keep going down, then we have test2's inclusion,
Here, in test2, we still have the inclusion of test1.
checking the ifndef of FT_TEST1_H,
this time it's been defined, so we won't include what's between
the "ifndef" and the "endif".
So we'll never re-include test2 again.
Going back to test2,
I'm still going down,
Here, I have to write this.
I get out of test2, go into test1, going back to test1.
I have to write this.
and I'm done including test1
in my main.
So here, you can see we included test2 and test1.
There hasn't been an infinite loop.
Normally, just to be thorough,
We should have protected test2 too, by adding...
this should be a reflex to you, now.
You should start protecting your files.h as soon as you create them.
By adding...
this ...
Piece of advice: learn to create macros with vim or emacs,
and create a script that does it automatically.
It'll be a time-saviour.
So, be careful.
Be really careful.
You'll see,
Once you've defined FT_TEST2 for example,
You can use it further into the code.
And watch out, this could be dangerous,
Because, imagine, in my main.
I don't know why anyone would do this,
But in my main, here,
if I do #ifndef, __FT_TEST2_H__.
if it hasn't been defined, I'm going to display my main.
And you'll see that if I do CPP,
my main had gone...
Because, once we've defined it anywhere really,
you see that my files have been added to my .c file.
And now, it's defined forever.
So if there are other things using the same macro,
well... the same define,
well, the "ifndef" won't work. The "ifdef" will work.
So be careful to set the right names,
otherwise, you'll have serious problems,
That's it. Now you know
how to protect your files.h against multiple inclusion.