Hello,
In this video, I'm going to show you how to create macros
with the preprocessor, using the preprocessor command: "define".
So to use the command "define",
you just need #define,
and the name of your preprocessor command. For example "TOTO".
and specify what it'll be replaced with.
Be careful, a #define replaces exactly
word per word, what you wrote on the right
except in particular cases you'' learn about later on.
Because we can create intelligent macros.
So imagine that I want "TOTO" to be replaced by an int.
So, as soon as I write "TOTO" anywhere,
(E.g.: I'm going to write it here)
during pre-compilation, so "cpp main.c"
my "TOTO" has been replaced by an int
I could write anything,
I could, for example, write jibberish,
during the pre-compilation phase, aka during pre-processing,
It doesn't think about what it does.
It just takes my macro, and replace it word by word.
So that's good, because we can create macros like this
which will allow us to do things, for example, if we wanted to
replace the int, and instead,
write "TOTO", you can do so.
You could, for example, write a text, any text,
let's say "Bonjour, bienvenue" ("Hello, welcome")
As soon as you write "TOTO, it'll be replaced by the string
"Bonjour, bienvenue" - with quotation marks -
That means that if I wrote this,
I'll put back my int here,
if I set a "char *str" here,
and then say that str = "TOTO",
here's what'd happen:
see, str is equal to "Bonjour, bienvenue"
so you could, for example, write sentences at the top of your files,
or even put them in a file.h,
and use that same sentence in multiple functions,
this way you'll have at least one macro
and you can change it in one place, and the rest will follow.
It's the same principle as functions' prototypes in files.h.
The other advantage of macros, is that you can make them intelligent...
and so you can use brackets and pass parameters,
you'll see these parameters will be replaced.
For example: I want to pass parameters "x"
and every time I'll write "TOTO()" with something between brackets,
I'll replace it by
"int x". You'll see what it could do.
I don't advise you to write it this way, because it's hard to read,
but it's one of #define's usage.
Here I'm going to declare a variable "a". I don't even need to add the ";"
a variable "b",
and here's what happens when I do "cpp main.c"
"int a; int b;"
You can see that my code is less legible this way.
So I don't advise you to do these kind of things.
The define will also allow you to link strings, for example.
Watch out, though, it's a little more complicated.
That's the last example I'll show you.
You could write "#x"
and "#x" means it would replace the brackets' content in "TOTO()"
by the value of what's in TOTO()'s brackets.
For example, if I added a "char *str" here
and say that "str" is equal to ...
"str" is equal to this.
Now, if I wrote "write(1, str, 1)",
What I'm going to display on screen,
theoretically,
I'm gonna display "a" onscreen.
Now, if instead this I wrote ... "b" ...
I could display "b".
One last example, just to make it cristal clear.
if I wrote...
"Bonjour les aminches". ("Hello frienchs")
we may have a problem with spaces. We never know...
I'm gonna check if it works. Looks like it
I do indeed have "b".
If now, I changed my write() and instead of 1, I picked 10,
I think "Bonjour les aminches" is longer than 10.
We can see that the TOTO() string has been replaced by the string between brackets.
We can then assemble macros,
I'm gonna show you another simple example.
So, for example, #define
we could call it "TITI(x)"
which will call "TOTO(x)",
semi-colon
"TOTO(x)".
Dunno. That's gonna make a mess.
Let me show you.
So "cpp main.c"
and here you can see,
Oh yeah, that's because I called "TOTO" and not "TITI"!
Here you can see we have the same string twice.
So CPP hasn't transformed this into a string.
but this means that soon it will become a string.
You can see we have our "TOTO" twice, and that we can assemble #defines together
and preprocessors will run as many time as needed,
until there's no "define" left.
What you need to remember, is that a "define" allows you to change
a macro, word by word, by the content of your choosing.