Today you'll find out that there are tools,
that allow you to script your compilation,
thanks to a specific language.
The command make is one of them,
although it's not the only tool at your disposal
I strongly advise you to run a search on
the internet and check out other tools,
and why not try and learn how to use them.
Anyhow...
Today we're going to focus on make and Makefiles.
The command make goes along
with one, or several, Makefiles files.
Those files will describe, using a set of rules,
how to compile your program.
So, we use the command make
which will call the Makefile,
read it, and execute it.
A Makefile simply is a file named Makefile
which contains a set of rules
as well as some variables
that describe the behaviour
the compilation must adopt.
Of course, the rules will be able
to call themselves,
and will be able to use variables...
The most important thing
is to properly structure all of this
in order to reach our goal.
Let's assume that our Makefile
contains the rule clean,
to call this rule, I just have to type :
"make clean" in my terminal.
You need to know that all of the rules in a Makefile,
are not there to be executed
every time we use the command make.
Usually, only one rule is executed
and its dependencies (we'll see this later)
in order to perform the actions
this rule was created for.
make's syntax is rather simple,
yet very powerful, and we'll discover it
in the next part of this course.
I'm not saying this lesson on Makefiles
will be exhaustive or perfect.
I just want to show you the technology
and lay the most basic basis
so you can get by,
but you'll learn much more on Makefiles
by reading documentation on the internet.
See you in the next video.
We'll discover the basics of Makefile's syntax