Makefile rules have a
very simple syntax.
They are made of a name,
of a dependencies list,
as well as of a definition of the rule,
which is made of several Shell command lines.
Let's write an example together.
I'm going to edit a file named Makefile,
be careful here, it always starts
with an uppercase "M".
Let me set my header.
And now I can write my first rule.
I'm going to call it "regle_a",
/ in french "regle" means "rule" \
and add a colon
and immediatly after this colon
I'll be able to write a list of rules
I want to execute before "regle_a".
We'll get back to that later on.
The rule's list of definitions
(Shell commands to be executed)
starts on the line right after the rule's name.
Each line must start with a tabulation.
If I want "regle_a" to write something
I'll use the echo command
and make it write, for example, "regle a".
I backup my Makefile, & can now use make,
specifying my rule's name, "regle_a".
We can see that ...
the Makefile has displayed
the line 'echo "regle a"'
That's exactly what I wrote.
You need to know that when a Makefile rule is executed,
each Shell command line will be displayed
on your terminal, before execution.
That's why we can see "echo regle a"
an then "regle a".
You can prevent this behavior,
by adding "@" just before the command,
thus the command line won't be displayed
before being executed.
Let's go back to our Makefile
and define a new rule
"regle_b".
and set "regle_a" as a dependency, so that
"regle_a" is executed before "regle_b".
And I want "regle_b" to display "regle b".
(using echo)
Saving my Makefile...
executing my "regle_b".
Since my "regle_b" has "regle_a" as a dependency
"make" first executed "regle_a",
we can see "regle a",
then executed "regle_b"
("regle b" is displayed).
This way, a rule can call another
to solve its dependencies,
and we'll be able to instantiate variables,
change contents, etc.
Now that we've seen how to define rules in a Makefile,
we're going to learn, in the next session,
how to define variables,
and how to use them in your Makefile
to improve your program's semantics.