You now know how to use pointers to functions in C.
What you need to understand is that the goal isn't to
make you use pointers to functions everywhere,
or any old how.
Pointers to functions are for specific cases
which you'll learn to identify
with experience.
I strongly advise you to do some research on the internet
and find other ways to exploit this notion.
The Internet holds many examples and tutorials, and everything
you could possibly need to master this notion.
I really strongly advise you to do so, because pointers to functions
is a notion you'll come across a lot, later on,
under a slightly different shape, when you'll learn C++,
and we'll see that it's a notion at the center of many problems,
and that needs to be mastered.
So it's important to start right away,
by understanding how to use pointers to functions,
and know what they truly conceal.
But that's your responsibility, so good luck for today's exercises
and see you very soon for another video.
Goodbye.