You now know how to declare and use a pointer to function
in your programs.
But you may be wondering what's the point of this,
because if we already have the possibility to call functions in
a normal way, why bother using a complicated syntax to be able to
call them via a pointer to function.
This is an excellent question, and of course,
you can still use this technique.
However, you have to remember that, as you'll discover,
there are certain particular cases where pointers to function
can be really helpful but mostly, they can render your code
more readable and more stable.
How about I show you some examples?
These example will show you that pointers to functions are totally
appropriate for our solution.
What you need to understand, before checking out the example,
is that I chose to show it to you in pseudo-code, and not in C,
because if I showed you the real code in C,
you'd have all the answers for today's exercises,
and you know it's not the point.
So, today we're going to see a syntax that doesn't exist,
that I've invented for this demonstration.
Just enough for you to get how to use
pointers to function.
You'll have to transcribe this example in C,
in order to use it normally. But that's something you'll do on your own.
The example I'm offering is to imagine we're in a situation
where we have 3 functions which allow us
to write an arbitrary data,
either on the standard output, thanks to put_stdout(),
either in a file, thanks to put_file(),
either on the network, thanks to put_network().
Let's imagine we have these functions. They're implemented and are
perfectly functional.
Here, our goal will be to write a function "put" which will take 2 parameters.
The 1st is a parameter I've called "where"
which will allow us to know on which output to write : STDOUT,
a file, or the network.
The 2nd parameter, "what", represents
the data to write.
The exact type of this data isn't important, here,
it's just to say that it exists.
The naive approach, as the one you'd have had before today,
would be to write something like " if "where" is worth STDOUT,
then I'll call put_stdout(), with "what" as a parameter,
or else, if "where" is a file ... " See where I'm going with this.
The problem here, is that every time
you want to add a possible destination, for example, with a function
put_stderr() to write on the error output,
I'm gonna have to position myself here, and add an "else if", etc...
We realise that we're basically
growing an entire forest of IFs
and it's unacceptable
to write ugly things like this in your code.
A clean and efficient solution to this problematic
is to use a set of pointers to functions
to be able to call the right function.
Let's see what we have here.
We have 3 functions:put_stdout(), put_file() and put_network(),
which will all have the same prototype.
They don't return anything in particular, and all take the argument "what"
as a parameter, to write it where it should.
So it'll be possible for us to regroup a bunch of pointers to these functions
in an array, and associate to each entry
the moment we'll want to use it, and so, if we're asked for an STDOUT,
a file or a network, and, in pair, the function to use in this case.
The pseudo-code would look something like this.
Let's imagine our array of pointers to functions,
which would be made of a list of pairs, for example an array of pairs,
or what you want to do in C, where we'd have, as a first information.
where to write, in which case selecting this array's entry,
and as a second info, a pointer to the function that needs to be used
in this case.
Which will allow us, below, in our function put(),
to lighten the code, and make it much more practical,
keeping in mind we're still taking "where" and "what" as parameters,
then we'll simply do a loop.
In my pseudo-code, I've used the keyword "for",
but you'll use "while", or recursion, up to you.
So, for each entry in my array, I'm gonna have a couple
the "where" of reference, and the function put_...() associated,
and I'll check whether the "where" that I was asked to use
corresponds to the "where" in our array.
If it's the case, then I'll use the associated put_...() function,
else, if nothing happens, the array keeps looping
until we find the right function, or if we don't, we'll have to
handle error cases, but this is going
further than this exercise's goal.
This is a canonic shape in programming.
You'll realise that you'll sometimes come across
this kind of situation, and in those moments, it could be interesting
to remember pointers to functions, to know how to use them appropriately.
See you in a moment for the conclusion of today's lesson.