Now that you've seen every thing about
chained lists,
Let me give you some tips
There are many ways to write add_link().
We can write it like this,
with an int to return different error codes, for example,
and a double pointer to list as another parameter,
as well as our char *str, to fill up our link.
What does this mean?
It means that when we'll call our add_link(), from our main,
(let's write add_link())
and return the address of 'list',
with, for example, "titi".
If we do this... as we already had a pointer,
and send this pointer's address, we get a double pointer.
Remember pointers.
We know that, for example, if we have an int "i" that's worth 10,
we can create an int*, let's say "p", that'll contain the address of "i".
What happens with a double pointer?
We're gonna get an int**, e.g.: "pp", that contains the address of "p".
Meaning...
that the function called, can modify
our pointer's address, in the calling function.
In other words...
by erasing all of this, I could simply write:
*list = malloc
and so "list" will point towards a valid memory area.
and will be set (initialised) automatically, in your function main().
Good luck.