We know that we need to define
our structure in order to use it
as a link in our list.
So let's create our .h
and we protect it from multiple inclusion.
What I like here,
is that we can create a typedef on the future defintion of our list.
Thus we can write struct s_list
Let's say it contains a "char *str",
and like I said
a pointer to a struct s_list next.
Thanks to my typedef,
I can write this here.
Now
let's get to our function "main".
We'll need our list definition
so we include list.h,
we return (0).
Due to the fact that we're using a list,
we're going to create a pointer "list" to our "t_list" type.
What do we do with that?
We're going to initialise it to NULL.
So we're gonna need stdlib.h.
Here.
I'll explain this later.
Let's say that list is equal to
a new link added to our list,
which will contain, for example, "toto".
We're going to repeat this operation,
but with "tata" this time,
and finally with "tutu", just for fun.
In order to test all of this,
we're going to create a function "print_list"
which will simply display what's in our list.
Don't forget to declare prototypes.
So "add_link" returns ... a t_list*,
and takes our list and a char *str as parameters,
to fill up our newly created links,
And finally, print_list
which takes a t_list * as a parameter.
Let's move on to "add_link".
What do you think "add_link" will do on our list?
Don't forget the .h inclusion.
It returns a t_list *
and takes our list as a parameter
- list to which it will add our link -
t_list *list and some data to fill it up with.
Here.
We'll need malloc here.
So we've got to include stdlib.h.
Good.
We know that we have to create a link.
Let's call it "tmp"
we return it... well, that's a bit useless
because we're going to segfault... So let's make tmp
point to a valid memory area with malloc.
tmp = malloc(sizeof *(t_list))
We can use the alias in sizeof.
If tmp is not NULL, then malloc was successful.
Therefore we can manipulate our link and fill it up.
let's say that the variable "str"
which is a pointer to char contained in our structure,
is equal to the str passed as a parameter.
Now let's say that tmp->next=list.
If tmp was null we would return NULL,
which would indicate an error,
Good.
What would happen
If I called this function for the first time?
I'm gonna create tmp,
and say that it contains "toto"
and that its "->next" points to list.
Except that list is equal to NULL
so it points to NULL.
The second time, I return list
which, this time, is equal to our first tmp,
I create a new tmp which contains "tata".
I say that its next points to list.
List is equal to our first tmp
So it's the same thing.
When we call for the 3rd time,
you know what I'm going to say,
I fill up tmp with "tutu"
and I say that its "next" points to list
which is now equal to our 2nd tmp.
Let's write print_list now
in order to check if everything works.
I'll just need list.h,
we don't return anything,
I take a t_list *list as a parameter.
So,
I want to display str, which is a char *
we're going to use ft_pustr(list->str)
not particularly difficult.
I'll have to print the data from all of my links,
so I'm gonna need a while
but how will it stop?
If I go back to my schema
the next is equal to the address
of our 2nd link in the list.
So if I do list->next, in our 3rd case,
list is here, containing "tutu",
->next brings us to the link containing "tata".
So I moved on to the 2nd element.
If I do ->next again, I will reach
the 3rd element which contains "toto".
Doing -> one more time, I'll reach
a pointer which points to NULL.
Looks like an exit condition...
So,
let's say that list=list->next
doing this, list->next will bring me to "tata"
list is now equal to the link
containing "tata".
If I do list->next again, I'll reach
the link containing "toto".
As long as list != NULL.
Let's compile and test this.
And if I launch the program, I have "tutu tata toto".
What does this mean?
The most perceptive of you will note
that I first created "toto", then "tata", and then "tutu",
but we can read "tutu", "tata", "toto".
Let's go back to my schema
We can notice that, every time,
the head of my list is moved to the element I just created.
Therefore, my list will be in reverse from the way I created it.