Let's now see how to open files in C.
For that, we use the system call "open",
which can take 2 or 3 parameters, depending on usage.
The first parameter is the file to open,
the path can be relative or absolute,
The 2nd is the opening mode : read only, write only, both,
and the permissions, in case of new file creation.
"open" will either return an int, corresponding to the
open File Descriptor, or -1 in case of error.
Before showing you (with code) how to open a file,
let me first talk about flags.
As I've mentioned, we have 3 flags that allow us to control
the level of access to the file :
O_RDONLY -> open read only.
O_WRONLY -> open write only.
and O_RDWR -> open read write.
We've also got flags that allow us
to modify OPEN's behavior, such as
O_CREAT, which allows us to create a
file, if it doesn't exists yet.
Flags can be combined with a binary OR,
and there are many others to use, check out the man.
Let's now move on to code.
In this very simple example, I've included the headers required by OPEN,
I've declared an int, called "fd", to which I've assigned OPEN's return
of a file "alph", that contains a few letters,
and in read only mode.
Then I get "fd" to be displayed, just to check I got a valid
file descriptor.
Let's compile this example.
"3" is being displayed.
Let's reopen the code.
So, OPEN has indeed returned 3, and I've displayed it.
The file is opened and I can manipulate it by using
this File Descriptor 3.
Now, let's see how to open a file in Write mode.
Let's get a file "42" created,
in write mode only, and get it to be created if it doesn't exist,
and to give me write and read permissions,
and to display the file descriptor.
Compiling...
"3" is displayed, so my file has indeed been opened.
A file "42" has indeed been created.
and I have read and write permissions on it.
Before moving on to the rest, let me show you how important
OPEN's return is.
Always check this! Let me remind you that
open returns -1 in case of error, and that you cannot
manipulate a file descriptor that's equal to -1.
So let's check that "fd" is not equal to -1.
I'll leave the putnbr(), so we can see
that the FD is equal to -1, and ask it to open a file
in a directory to which I don't have access: "/dev".
Recompiling.
Launching.
We can see that my FD is equal to -1,
that my OPEN hasn't worked, and so
I cannot manipulate my file.
Now, let me show you how to close a file.
For that, we have the system call CLOSE.
This one only takes a File Descriptor
as a parameter, and returns 0 normally, or -1 in case of error.
Reopening my code...
Putting back the "42" file.
I'll leave here, in case of error.
And then I'll close my file at the end of my code.
Recompiling.
"3". My file's been opened, and closed in a transparent manner.
This concludes this video on file opening and closing.
See you in the next video, where we'll see how to read from a file.