Now let's learn how to write in a file descriptor.
We'll use the system call
write, which takes 3 parameters.
The 1st parameter is the File Descriptor we'll write in.
The 2nd parameter is what we want to write.
The 3rd parameter is the number of bytes we need.
Write returns the number of bytes written
or -1 in case of error.
So here's my opening file function
and I'm gonna create a function ft_putchar()
which takes a file descriptor
and a character as parameters.
In the FD we'll write the character
in 1 byte.
I'll call this function
right after opening the file
to write a "z".
Compiling...
Launching...
The file "42" has been created,
it weighs 1 byte.
If we look inside, there is a "z".
Let's do it again.
There still is only one "z".
That's when the Open flags I was talking about earlier
come in to help us.
So we'll ask Open to open this file
in APPEND mode, which will allow us
to write from the last byte
in the file.
Compiling again.
Launching again...
And now there are 2 "z" in my file.
And now 3 !
Let's try to write something
more interesting than "z".
I'm going to rename my putchar function
to putstr_fd
which will take a pointer to character.
And ask it to write "Hello World".
Recompiling...
Relaunching...
and now there is "Hello World"
entirely written in my file '42'.
I can launch it many times
it'll write the words each time.
This concludes the part about writing in a File Descriptor.
In the next video we'll learn how to read from a file.