In this video we'll learn
how to read from a File Descriptor.
We'll use the system call Read,
which takes 3 parameters.
The 1st one is the File Descriptor
from which we'll read from,
the 2nd one is the output buffer,
and the last one is the number of bytes needed to read.
Read returns the number of bytes that have been read
or -1 on error.
Here's an example.
I've reopened my opening file function.
My file '42' is open in read-only mode
I'm gonna set the buffer size to 4096,
create an Int to stock the Read's return
and the buffer, which is static
but you could also create it with Malloc.
Adding a byte... You'll see why.
I ask Read to read 4096 bytes from my file '42'
and save them in buff.
Don't forget the '\0' at the end of the string.
We're going to print the buffer
and the number of characters that have been read.
Compiling... Launching...
The buffer is displayed, I've read 31 bytes
much less than 4096.
In some cases, you won't know
how many bytes are needed
you'll have to use a loop on Read.
Read returns 0 when it reaches the end of the file,
use this condition for your loop.
Let's set a limit of 10 characters.
The file is 33 characters long...
Recompiling... Relaunching...
In each loop, Read returns 10 characters
and returns 0 once the last one has been reached.
Then we get out of the loop.
This concludes the part about reading from a File Descriptor.
In the next video, we'll talk about offset.