In this second video, I'm going to show
you how to solve the problem
we've come across in the first video,
by balancing our binary trees.
Reminder:
we've seen that a tree such this one
lost all of its interests,
we can easily guess why,
and we'd rather have
this type of tree, which is much
more balanced.
A little uglier, but more balanced.
So here, we can see that several
nodes have one child,
sometimes they have 2,
and there's about the same number
of elements on either sides.
So the search-time will always
be optimal.
The only disadvantages of this tree,
are that you'll have to
struggle to balance it, as well as
the insertion and removal will
be a little longer.
To balance it, we'll use what we call
a Red-black tree.
I'll show you what it looks like in C.
It looks like this.
Moreover, we have an enum which
defines the node's color.
Black or red.
The structure is the same, but we've
added the field "color".
There's an advantage in keeping the
same structure:
we'll be able to tell the compiler
that our structure
is a struct s_btree.
And it'll reply
"ok, no worries mate, I'll do it".
So you'll be able to use all the
traversal-functions you've
created for simple btrees.
It'll spare you having to re-write
loads of code, when the treatment
is exactly the same, and the structure
is almost the same.
That's called polymorphism.
That's a pretty primary shape in C,
we can do much more,
but you'll discover that on your own.
Why red? Why black?
Let me explain, with some theory.
Red and black trees have several
properties.
The 1st, is that the parent node,
the tree's root, is black.
The 2nd, is that all leaves, including
those that are NULL,
are empty leaves,
they're also black. Just like the root.
3rd property says that a red node only has
black paths.
Either they're both NULL, either
they're real nodes, but black,
either a mix of both.
You see the idea.
The last property,
the most interesting one,
is that from whichever node of the tree,
the amount of black nodes
crossed (distance), between this node and
the last leaf is the same for
every leaf of this node.
Basically, this means the tree is balanced
It's a bit hard to get...
Now, the insertion.
This, we'll ask you to do,
as well as the removal.
I'm only going to show you one case
of insertion,
for other cases, you can do your
own research on the internet,
where it'll be explained much better,
and where you'll find better diagrams.
I'm just going to show you a simple
case of insertion,
which requires two operations,
you're going to use :
changing node color,
and tree rotation.
Let me show you.
To insert, in a red-black binary tree,
we first proceed to an insertion
like in a basic binary tree,
so by dichotomy.
In the diagram, "G" means grand-parents,
it's the node's grand-parent.
"P" = parents, "U" = uncle,
"N" is the node we've just inserted.
The colors are in parenthesis :
Black or Red.
After having done our basic insertion,
imagine we get this tree.
The node is red, because by default,
all nodes are red.
We can see that this tree doesn't respect
the properties of red-black trees.
The "P" is red, and should have two
black children, but only has one,
the one that's NULL.
The other is red.
Let's proceed to something quite
complicated.
Because the uncle is black and the
father is red.
So let's do something to balance it.
It's a particular case, there are
four or five like this.
So let's rotate the tree.
We're going to rotate to the right,
around "G".
You may want to put on your seat-belts.
Post-rotation, we get what's bellow.
"G" is where "U" used to be,
with "U" still under it,
because it's still a binary tree,
and "P" is now above "G".
If you think about it, you'll notice that
if I do this to my tree at the beginning,
it'll still be valid,
and we'll still be able to traverse it
in depth,
and it'll still be sorted.
In the end, "G" is bigger than "P",
so we'll be able to move it
bellow on the right.
And we happen to be in this case.
But we're breaking the rules of
red-black trees.,
because the parent is red, not black.
So, let's proceed to a color change
between "P" and "G",
it'll look like the following diagram.
"P" is at the root of the tree,
so it becomes black,
and "G" becomes red.
This way, we have a balanced binary tree.
Keep in mind that
this is not the only case of insertions.
There are 4 or 5, I think.
But you'll see for yourselves.
Every time you make an insertion,
you must check the tree
recursively, to make sure you haven't
messed it up.
For example, the fact that this one is
black or red could infringe
one of the properties, forcing you to
make more changes.
Normally, we get by with
2 rotations and 2-3 color changes,
in the worst case scenario.
The other cases,
you'll find them yourselves, as well as
cases of removal.
And to finish this video,
I'm going to give you some advice.
The first is for you to create a
function which displays your tree.
The first element and the two
following ones, etc...
I also advise you to display nodes
that are NULL too,
and to keep unfolding them.
It'll allow you to debug all your
functions, and check
whether your insertion went well,
and if the tree is balanced.
It takes time to code this, but it's
quite practical.
The second advice is to read thoroughly
whatever you find on the internet.
Binary trees are used a lot
and you'll find a lot of material
on the subject.
Which will probably be clearer than
this video, and will surely help better.
Good day.